<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Immorality, debauchery, and profaneness, exposed to the reproof of Scripture, and the censure of the law containing a compendium of the penal laws now in force against idleness, profaneness, and drunkenness, houses of unlawful games, profane swearing and cursing, speaking or acting in contempt of the Holy Sacrament, disturbing of ministers, profane jesting with the name of God, absenting form the church, profanation of the Lord's day, debauched incontinency, and bastard-getting : with several texts of Scripture prohibiting such vices : also a brief collection of several signal judgments of God against offenders in the said vices and debaucheries / published for the advancement of reformation of manners, so happily begun and carried on by several societies, by G. Meriton, Gent.</title>
            <author>Meriton, George, 1634-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11859091</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11859091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50664)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 502:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Immorality, debauchery, and profaneness, exposed to the reproof of Scripture, and the censure of the law containing a compendium of the penal laws now in force against idleness, profaneness, and drunkenness, houses of unlawful games, profane swearing and cursing, speaking or acting in contempt of the Holy Sacrament, disturbing of ministers, profane jesting with the name of God, absenting form the church, profanation of the Lord's day, debauched incontinency, and bastard-getting : with several texts of Scripture prohibiting such vices : also a brief collection of several signal judgments of God against offenders in the said vices and debaucheries / published for the advancement of reformation of manners, so happily begun and carried on by several societies, by G. Meriton, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Meriton, George, 1634-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>viii, 9-119, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Harris and Andrew Bell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law (Theology)</term>
               <term>Conduct of life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49981:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:49981:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Immorality, Debauchery,</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> Expoſed</p>
            <p>To the Reproof of Scripture, and the Cenſure of the Law.</p>
            <p>Containing a Compendium of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> now in Force againſt Idleneſs, Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Drunkenneſs; Houſes of unlawful Games; profane Swearing and Curſing; ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or acting in contempt of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; diſturbing of Miniſters; profane jeſting with the Name of God; abſenting from the Church; profanation of the Lord's Day; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched Incontinency, and Baſtard-getting.</p>
            <p>With ſeveral Texts of Scripture prohibiting ſuch Vices.</p>
            <p>Alſo a brief Collection of ſeveral ſignal Judgments of God againſt Offenders in the ſaid Vices and Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Advancement of <hi>Reformation of Manners,</hi> ſo happily begun and carried on by ſeveral Societies.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. MERITON,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation, but Sin is a Reproach to any People,</hi> 
               <bibl>Prov. 14. 34.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>God will wound the head of his Enemies, and the hairy Scalp of ſuch a one as goeth on ſtill in his Wickedneſs.</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 68. 21.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Harris</hi> and <hi>Andrew Bell,</hi> at the Harrow in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> and at the Croſs-keys and Bible in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49981:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:49981:2"/>
            <p>To the Honourable PAUL FOLEY, <abbr>Esq</abbr> SPEAKER OF THE <hi>Honourable Houſe of Commons,</hi> And to the reſt of the Honourable and Worthy Members of that High Council of the Realm now aſſembled in Parliament, This COMPENDIUM is humbly dedicated by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. MERITON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49981:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:49981:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Gracious Soveraign, King <hi>William,</hi> having obſerved the ſpreading growth of profane, vitious and profligate Debauchery and Immorality within this Realm; out of his devout and pious Zeal for the Honour of God, the advancement of true Religion, and the Credit and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of this his Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in his moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Speech to both the Houſes of Parliament, at the opening of this preſent Seſſion, tells them, That he eſteems it one of the greateſt Advantages of Peace, that he ſhall now have leiſure to rectify ſuch Corruptions or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, as may have crept into any part of the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration during the War, and effectually to diſcourage Profaneneſs and Immorality.</p>
            <p>And to that purpoſe his Majeſty has not only iſſued out his Proclamation for the diſcouraging of all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, Profaneneſs and Immorality; and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame to be read in every Church, and publick Chappel, four times in the year; but has alſo required all his Judges, Juſtices of the Peace, and other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Officers, within their ſeveral Limits and
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:49981:4"/>
Juriſdictions, according to their ſeveral Powers and Authorities, to put the Laws made againſt Profaneneſs and Immorality, effectually in execution. And has likewiſe recommended the further Care of the more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual ſuppreſſing Debauchery, Profaneneſs and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality, to the Conſideration of the Parliament, who have prepared a Bill for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And every good Chriſtian ought devoutly to join with the Church in that Prayer appointed by her Liturgy, to be read for the Parliament when ſitting; <hi>That God would be pleaſed to direct and proſper all their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations, to the advancement of his Glory, the good of his Church, the Safety, Honour, and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of our Soveraign and his Kingdoms; that all things may be ſo ordered and ſettled by their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, upon the beſt and ſureſt Foundations, that Peace and Happineſs, Truth and Juſtice, Religion and Piety, may be eſtabliſhed among us for all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations.</hi> And as every one ought thus to pray; ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo every individual Perſon within this Realm, ought <hi>(as a Reverend and Grave Divine lately declared in his Pulpit)</hi> according to his Capacity, and the Poſt he is placed in, to contribute his Help and Aſſiſtance towards the carrying on this great and pious work of Reformation. In compliance wherewith, and to manifeſt my good Will by contributing towards the carrying on this great and good Work, I have compil'd this <hi>Eſſay</hi> as a Compendium of the Laws now in force againſt Idleneſs, Profaneneſs, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and for the more effectual enforcing the Obſervation of the ſame. I have after the ſaid Laws, ſet down ſeveral Texts of Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Sins: and after them (leſt ſome by their long continued wicked Courſes be ſo hardned in their Sins, that neither Law nor Goſpel will reſtrain them) I have given an Account of ſeveral exemplary Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, upon ſuch as have accuſtomed themſelves in the practice of ſuch profane Vices; in hopes that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the peruſal thereof, ſuch as walk and tread in the
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:49981:4"/>
ſame Steps, may be brought to a ſight and ſenſe of their Sins, repent of their Wickedneſs, and reſolve to lead a new Courſe of Life.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other Laws againſt ſuſpicious Perſons that walk by Night, and ſleep by Day, keep lewd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and frequent lewd Houſes. 39 <hi>Eliz. Ch.</hi> 4. 43 <hi>Eliz. Ch.</hi> 2. 7 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 4. and againſt wandring Rogues, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 7. But the other Vices aforementioned, being the cuſtomary and provoking Sins of the Nation, and theſe others laſt mentioned, not ſo common; and the Laws made againſt them not ſo properly falling under the Title of this Compendium, I have therefore purpoſely omitted the inſerting of them. And ſuch Readers as are deſirous to inform themſelves herein, may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the ſeveral Statutes as they are here cited. But I ſhall proceed no further, only deſire that this ſmall Treatiſe may in ſome meaſure effect its intended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and prove ſerviceable to the Publick; which is the hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. Meriton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:49981:5"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the Authors Names out of whoſe Works the ſignal Examples of God's ſevere Juſtice, mentioned in this enſuing Treatiſe, are excerpted.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ABbot.</item>
               <item>Anton. de Torquenda.</item>
               <item>Auguſtinus.</item>
               <item>Baxter.</item>
               <item>Beadle.</item>
               <item>Batman.</item>
               <item>Baker.</item>
               <item>Beard.</item>
               <item>Bernard.</item>
               <item>Beza.</item>
               <item>Bolton.</item>
               <item>Burton.</item>
               <item>Clark, Camden.</item>
               <item>Diſcipulus de Tempore.</item>
               <item>Euſebius.</item>
               <item>Fauconer.</item>
               <item>Fox.</item>
               <item>Gregory Tomonenſis.</item>
               <item>German Hiſtory.</item>
               <item>Heylin.</item>
               <item>Heywood.</item>
               <item>Johan. Wierus.</item>
               <item>Johan. Fincelius.</item>
               <item>Lonicerus.</item>
               <item>Luther.</item>
               <item>Laertius.</item>
               <item>Maginus.</item>
               <item>Platina.</item>
               <item>Perkins.</item>
               <item>Quintus Curtius.</item>
               <item>Socrates.</item>
               <item>Spotſwood.</item>
               <item>Speed.</item>
               <item>Stanley.</item>
               <item>Stow.</item>
               <item>Teate.</item>
               <item>Theatr. Hiſtoriarum.</item>
               <item>Turner.</item>
               <item>Twiſden.</item>
               <item>Ward.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49981:5"/>
            <head>THE Laws againſt Profaneneſs.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſummary Account of the Laws made againſt profuſe, idle, cuſtomary and expenſive Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and againſt ſinful, cuſtomary and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Drunkenneſs; and againſt keeping Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or Houſes of unlawful Games.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SOme of our Chronologers tell us, that the <hi>Danes</hi> were the firſt and principal Introducers and Promoters of the immoderate, profuſe and ſinful Vice of exceſſive Carouſing, Quaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing and Drinking, which by their Example did ſo influence the People of this Kingdom, that in a ſmall time it arrived to that height of Vanity, that <hi>Edgar</hi> the ſeventeenth King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> and firſt ſole Saxon Monarch of <hi>England,</hi> in order to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining and curbing the growth of the ſaid debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Vanity and ſinful Vice, did ordain certain Cups or Pots, with Gages, Pins or Marks in them, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Penalty to be inflicted upon every one that ſhould preſume to drink beyond the limited Gage; which Ordinance of his poſſibly might in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure abate the exorbitant Practice of this growing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49981:6"/>
Wickedneſs; yet the Practice thereof was never wholly laid aſide, eſpecially in the times of Peace and Tranquillity.</p>
               <p>And upon the Union of the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the Acceſſion of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt to the Crown of this Realm, the Minds and Hearts of the People were ſo elevated with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and great aſſurances they propounded to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the future Tranquillity, Peace, Plenty, Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and great Proſperity that in all probability was thereby likely to enſue, that they thereupon became leſs induſtrious and laborious in their ſeveral Callings, Trades, Arts, Myſteries, Profeſſions, and ways of getting their Livelihoods, and did much indulge themſelves in the pleaſant enjoyment of frequent and frolick Society, by them call'd Good-fellowſhip, which oft-times happened to be with ſuch expence of Time and Money too, that many of their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies became much impoveriſhed thereby: And the antient, true and principal uſe of Inns, Alehouſes, and Victualing-houſes being for the Receipt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Lodging of ſuch People as are not able by greater quantities to make their Proviſion of Victuals, became common Tipling Houſes, and places of Entertainment, and Harbour of lewd and idle People, to ſpend and conſume their Money and their Time in lewd and drunken manner, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true meaning of the principal intended Purpoſes of ſuch Houſes; as the Parliament the firſt Year of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt obſerves.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>It is therefore enacted by the ſaid Parliament, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 9. That if any Inn-keeper, Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualer or Alehouſe-keeper within the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> do permit or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49981:6"/>
ſuffer any Perſon or Perſons inhabiting or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in any City, Town Corporate, Village or Hamlet within the ſaid Realm, or Dominions, where any ſuch Inn, Alehouſe or Victualing-houſe is or ſhall be, to remain and continue drinking or tipling in the ſame, other than ſuch as ſhall be invited by any Traveller, and ſhall accompany him only during his neceſſary Abode there, and other than labouring and Handicrafts-men in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Towns Corporate, and Market Towns, upon the uſual working days, for one hour at Dinner-time, to take their Diet in an Alehouſe; and other than Labourers and Workmen which for the following of their Work by the day, or by the great, in any City, Town Corporate, Market-Town, or Village, ſhall for the time of their ſaid continuing in work there, ſojourn, lodg, or victual in any Inn, Alehouſe, or Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aling-houſe, other than for urgent and neceſſary occaſions to be allowed by two Juſtices of the Peace: That then every ſuch Innkeeper, Victualer, and Alehouſe-keeper, ſhall for every ſuch Offence forfeit and loſe the Sum of Ten Shillings of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Money of <hi>England,</hi> to the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh where ſuch Offence ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; the ſame Offence being view'd and ſeen by any Mayor, Bailiff, or Juſtice of Peace within their ſeveral Limits, or proved by the Oaths of two Witneſſes to be taken before any Mayor, Bailiff, or any other head Officer, or any one or more Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace, who are authorized to adminiſter the ſame within the Limits of their Commiſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49981:7"/>
The ſaid Penalties to be levied by the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or Church-wardens of the Pariſh or Pariſhes where the Offence or Offences ſhall be committed, by way of Diſtreſs, to be taken and detain'd for the ſaid Forfeiture; and for default of Satisfaction within ſix days next enſuing, the ſame then to be preſently apprized and ſold, and the Surpluſage or Remainder over and above, to be deliver'd to the Party diſtrained: and for want of ſufficient Diſtreſs, the Offenders to be by the Mayor, Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, or other head Officer, or Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace aforeſaid, committed to the common Goal, there to remain until the ſame Penalty be truly paid.</p>
                  <p>If the Conſtable or Church-wardens neglect their Duty in levying, or in default of Diſtreſs, do neglect to certify the default of Diſtreſs, by the ſpace of twenty days then next enſuing, to the Magiſtrates aforeſaid, within whoſe Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction the Offence is committed; then every Perſon ſo offending, ſhall forfeit for every ſuch default, the Sum of Forty Shillings, to the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh where ſuch Offence ſhall be committed, to be levied by Diſtreſs and Sale of the Offender's Goods, by Warrant from any ſuch Magiſtrate within the Limits of their Juriſdictions reſpectively, under his Hand and Seal, if Payment be not made within ſix days next enſuing the taking of the ſaid Diſtreſs; and the Surpluſage (if any be) to be delivered to the Party diſtrained; and for want of ſufficient, the Conſtable or Church-wardens ſo offending, to be by ſuch Magiſtrate committed to the common Goal, there to remain until the ſaid Penalty or Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties be truly paid.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49981:7"/>
Notwithſtanding the Reſtraint put upon Inn-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Victualers and Alehouſe-keepers by the Act of Parliament aforementioned, and the Penalty to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred by them, for ſuffering Tipling in their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the People did ſtill continue their Bowſing, Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and Carouſing, which by little and little arrived to that height of Exceſs, that it uſually ended (and does ſo ſtill) in downright Drunkenneſs, and grew ſo habitual and practicable, that it was (and ſtill is) even in a manner become an Epidemical Vice through the whole Realm: for Puniſhing and Suppreſſing of which odious Sin, in the fourth year of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, an Act of Parliament was made, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting a Penalty upon Drunkards, and ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue drinking in Ale-houſes. In the preamble of which Act, the Parliament takes notice of ſeveral Sins occaſioned by, and proceeding from Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as appears by what follows.</p>
               <p>Stat. 4 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 5.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Whereas the loathſom and odious Sin of Drunkenneſs is of late years grown into common uſe within this Realm, being the Root and Foundation of many other enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Sins, as Bloodſhed, Stabbing, Murder, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Fornication, Adultery, and ſuch like, to the great diſhonour of God, and of the Nation; the overthrow of many good Arts, and manual Trades; the diſabling of divers Workmen, and the general impoveriſhing of many good Subjects, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſively waſting the good Creatures of God:</p>
                  <p>It is therefore Enacted, That all and every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Perſons that ſhall be drunken, and of the ſame Offence of Drunkenneſs ſhall be lawfully Convicted, ſhall for every ſuch Offence forfeit and loſe five Shillings, to be paid within one Week
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49981:8"/>
next after Conviction, to the hands of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden of that Pariſh where the Offence ſhall be committed, who ſhall be accountable for it to the uſe of the ſaid Poor: and if the Perſons convicted refuſe or neglect to pay, then the ſame to be levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their Goods, by Warrant or Precept from the ſame Court, Judg, or Juſtices before whom the ſaid Conviction ſhall be: And if the Offenders be not able to pay the Penalty, then to be committed to the Stocks for every Offence, there to remain by the ſpace of ſix Hours.</p>
                  <p>And if any Officer of the Place where the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhall be committed, upon a Precept ſent to him, ſhall neglect his Duty in correcting the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, or in due Levying the Penalties where Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs may be had, then the Officer ſo offending ſhall forfeit ten Shillings to the uſe of the Poor there, to be levied by Diſtreſs by any Perſon or Perſons having Warrant from the Magiſtrate or Court where any Conviction ſhall be; and to be paid to the Church-wardens as before limited, who are to account for the ſame as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>And if any Perſon or Perſons within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> ſhall remain or continue Drinking, or Tipling, in any Inn, Victualing-houſe, or Ale-houſe, being in the ſame City, Town, Village, or Hamlet, wherein they dwell or inhabit at the time of ſuch Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Tipling, and the ſame being viewed or ſeen by any Mayor, or other head Officer, Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice or Juſtices of the Peace within their ſeveral Limits, or duly proved in ſuch manner and form as is limited in, and by the Act of Parliament, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 9. aforementioned, except it be in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49981:8"/>
ſuch Caſe or Caſes as be tolerated or excepted in the ſaid Act; That then every Perſon or Perſons ſo offending ſhall forfeit for every ſuch Offence, three Shillings and four Pence to the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh where the Offence ſhall be committed, to be levied by Diſtreſs in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and form as is before appointed by this Act, for the levying the Penalty of five Shillings for being Drunk; and the Offender being unable to pay, and being lawfully Convicted, then any of the Magiſtrates aforeſaid, or Court where any ſuch Conviction ſhall be, may puniſh the Offender or Offenders, by ſetting them in the Stocks for every ſuch Offence, by the ſpace of four Hours.</p>
                  <p>The Offences in this and the former mentioned Act, ſhall be inquired of, and preſented before the Juſtices of Aſſize in their Circuits, Juſtices of Peace in their ordinary Seſſions, and before the Mayor, Bailiffs, or other Head Officers of every City, or Town Corporate, who have Power to enquire of Treſpaſſes, Riots, Routs, and ſuch like Offences, and in every Court Leet; and ſuch Proceedings to be had thereupon againſt ſuch Offenders for their Conviction, as in ſuch like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is uſed by the Laws of the Realm, or Cuſtom of the City, Town, or Place, where ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment or Indictment ſhall be enquired of and found.</p>
                  <p>And if any Perſon or Perſons being once law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Convicted of the ſaid Offence of Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhall after that be again lawfully Convicted of the like Offence of Drunkenneſs; Then for ſuch ſecond Offence, they ſhall be bound with two Sureties to the King's Majeſty in one Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49981:9"/>
or Obligation of ten Pounds, with Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be from thenceforth of the good Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
                  <p>All Conſtables, Church-wardens, Headboroughs, Tything-men, Ale-Conners, and Side-men, ſhall in their ſeveral Oaths incident to their Offices, be charged to preſent the Offences contrary to this Act.</p>
                  <p>This Act is not to reſtrain the Eccleſiaſtical Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or Juriſdiction, nor the Liberty of either of the Univerſities, but that they enjoy their Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Rights, and Privileges.</p>
                  <p>And if any Offender againſt the true Intent and Meaning of this Act, or any Branch thereof, hath been once puniſhed or corrected for his or her Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, by any the Ways or Means before limited, he ſhall not be puniſhed or corrected for the ſaid Offence by any other Ways or Means.</p>
                  <p>And none ſhall be puniſhed or moleſted for any Offence mentioned in this Statute, unleſs he ſhall be Indicted, Preſented, or Convicted for the ſame within ſix Months after ſuch Offence committed.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Then by another Act of Parliament, 7 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10. It is Enacted <q>That if any Perſon being an Alehouſe-keeper, ſhall be lawfully Convicted for any Offence or Offences committed againſt any of the Branches of the two before mentioned Acts of Parliament, that then every Perſon or Perſons ſo Convicted, ſhall for the ſpace of three Years next enſuing the ſaid Conviction, be utterly diſabled to keep any ſuch Ale-houſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The two Statutes firſt mentioned in this Chapter, made againſt Tipling and Drunkenneſs, requiring proof to be made by two Witneſſes, for the more eaſy Conviction of ſuch Offenders:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49981:9"/>
It is by the Statute 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 7. Enacted, <q>That proof by one Witneſs ſhall be allowed and taken for ſufficient in that behalf; and the volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Confeſſion (before any ſuch Perſons as by the ſaid Acts are authorized to miniſter the Oath) of any Perſon offending either of the ſaid Statutes, ſhall ſuffice to convict the Perſon ſo offending; and after ſuch Confeſſion, the Oath of the party ſo offending, ſhall and may be taken, and be a ſufficient proof againſt any other offending at theſame time.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And it is further Enacted,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That if any Perſon or Perſons whereſoever his or their Habitation or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding be, ſhall at any time be found upon view, or his own Confeſſion, or proof of one Witneſs, to be Tipling in any Inn, Ale-houſe, or Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-houſe, ſuch Perſon or Perſons ſhall be within the meaning of the ſaid Statutes, as if ſuch Perſon had inhabited and dwelt in the ſame place, where the ſaid Inn, Ale-houſe, or Victualling-houſe is or ſhall be, where he or they ſhall be found Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ſhall incur the like Penalty; and the ſame to be levied and diſpoſed as in the ſaid Act is expreſſed, concerning ſuch as there inhabit; and the voluntary Confeſſion of the Offenders (before ſuch as by the ſaid Statutes are authorized to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Oath) ſhall ſuffice to convince them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And after ſuch Confeſſion, the Oath of ſuch Perſon or Perſons ſo confeſſing; ſhall and may be taken by ſuch as by the ſaid Act have Authority to miniſter the ſaid Oath, and ſhall be a ſufficient proof againſt any other offending at the ſame time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49981:10"/>
And any Juſtice of Peace in any County, and any Juſtice of Peace or other Head Officer in any City or Town Corporate within their Limits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, ſhall have Power and Authority upon his own View, Confeſſion of the party, or proof of one Witneſs upon Oath before him, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any Perſon of the offence of Drunkenneſs, whereby ſuch Perſon ſo convict, ſhall incur the forfeiture of five Shillings for every ſuch Offence; and the ſame to be levied, or the Offender other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe puniſhed, as in the Statute is appointed; and for the ſecond Offence ſhall become bound to the good Behaviour, as if he had been convicted in open Seſſions, any thing in the ſaid former Act, 4 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
                  <p>And if any Perſon being an Alehouſe-keeper, ſhall at any time be lawfully convicted for any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt any the Branches of either of the two former mentioned Statutes, according to the Alterations and Additions herein contained, againſt the true meaning of this Statute; then every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo convict, ſhall for the ſpace of three years next enſuing ſuch Conviction, be utterly diſabled to keep any ſuch Ale-houſe.</p>
                  <p>And Conſtables, Church-wardens, Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, Tything-men, Ale-conners, and Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, are to be charged in their Offices and Oaths to preſent all the Offences made in the Statute, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. againſt inordinate Haunting and Tipling in Inns, Ale-houſes, and other Victualling-houſes, according to the Alterations and Additions of the ſame in this Act contained.</p>
               </q>
               <p>There being no Penalty inflicted by the aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Act upon the Inn-keeper, Alehouſe-keeper or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49981:10"/>
Victualler that ſuffers Foreigners to Tipple in their Houſes:</p>
               <p>It is therefore 1 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 4. Enacted, <q>That every Inn-keeper, Alehouſe-keeper, or Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler that ſhall permit or ſuffer any Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not inhabiting in the City, Town Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, Market-Town, Village, or Hamlet, where ſuch Inn, Ale-houſe, or Victualling-houſe is, to Tipple in the ſaid Inn, Ale-houſe or Victualling-houſe, contrary to the true intent of any or either of the aforeſaid Statutes; the ſaid Inn-keeper, Alehouſe-keeper, and Victualler ſo offending, ſhall incur the ſame Penalty; and in ſuch manner to be proved, levied, and diſpoſed as in the former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 9. is appointed for permitting ſuch to tipple as dwell in the ſame City, Town Corporate, Market-Town, Village, or Hamlet.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And it is alſo Enacted, <q>That the keepers of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns, and ſuch as do ſell Wine in their Houſes, and do alſo keep Inns or Victualling-houſes, ſhall be taken to be within the ſaid two former Statutes, and alſo within this Statute.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe Laws againſt inordinate and cuſtomary Tippling and Drunkenneſs, were duly and effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put in Execution, it would not only be greatly to the Honour of God, but tend much to the Honour and Credit of this Realm: And might alſo prove very inſtrumental in the preventing many Families from Ruin, and becoming burdenſom and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Places where they live and are ſettled; for many ingenious Handicraft-men, and other labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and working Perſons, are ſo bewitch'd and charm'd with the love of ſtrong Drink, that what they earn with hard Labour all the day, having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49981:11"/>
regard to their own Credit, nor any Charity, Love or Kindneſs for their poor Wives and Families, they embezle and ſpend at Night, in profuſe, idle, and inſatiable Tipling and Drunkenneſs, amongſt their debauched Comrades, when at the ſame time perhaps their poor Families at home are ready to ſtarve for want of Bread.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore in the next Chapter acquaint theſe obſtinate, preſumptuous, and vitious Perſons, with ſome Texts of Scripture againſt theſe their ſinful Courſes, in hopes that the peruſal and ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of them, may bring them to a ſight and ſenſe of their Wickedneſs, and work ſome Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them.</p>
               <p>But before I proceed to the next Chapter, I think it will not be amiſs if we give a brief Account here, of the Laws made againſt Keepers of Play-houſes and unlawful Games; of which Offences many Inn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, Alehouſe-keepers and Victuallers' are guilty. By the Statute 33 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Ch.</hi> 9. it is Enacted,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That none ſhall keep or maintain any Houſe or Place of unlawful Games, on pain of forty Shillings every day. And none ſhall uſe or haunt ſuch places, on pain of ſix Shillings and eight Pence every time.</p>
                  <p>And it ſhall be lawful for every Juſtice of the Peace in every County, and for head Officers in Corporations, as well within the Liberties as without, to enter and reſort into all ſuch Houſes and Places, where ſuch unlawful Games are ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be uſed; and as well the Keepers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as the Reſorters thereto, to arreſt and impriſon until they ſhall ſeverally give good Security at the diſcretion of the ſaid Juſtices, or Officers, not to keep ſuch Games any more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49981:11"/>
Every Mayor, Sheriff, Bailiff, Conſtable, and other head Officer within every City, Borough or Town, ſhall make due Search as aforeſaid, once every Month at leaſt, on pain to forfeit 40 <hi>s.</hi> for every ſuch Default.</p>
                  <p>No Artificer or Journey-man, nor Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Apprentice, Labourer, Servant at Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Mariner, Fiſherman, Waterman, or Serving-man, ſhall play at Tables, Tenis, Dice, Cards, Bowls, Claſh, Goyting, Logating, or any other unlawful Game, out of <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> or then out of his Maſter's Houſe, or Preſence, on pain of twenty Shillings; and none ſhall play at Bowls in open Places, out of his Garden or Orchard, on pain of ſix Shillings and eight Pence.</p>
                  <p>All Informations or Suits upon this Statute ſhall be proſecuted within one year, and the Forfeitures thereof, which happen within a Leet or Liberty, ſhall be divided between the King and the Lord thereof; and in all other Places betwixt the King and the Proſecutor.</p>
                  <p>Proclamation of this Act ſhall be made quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly in every Market-Town, as alſo at every Goal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delivery, Aſſize and Seſſions</p>
                  <p>Then laſtly there is a Proviſo, that this Act ſhall not reſtrain a Servant (by his Maſter's Licenſe) to play at Cards, Dice, or Tables, with the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himſelf, or other Gentlemen reſorting to his Maſter's Houſe: and if the Maſter have Freehold of an hundred Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> he may alſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe his Servant to play at Bowls or Tenis.</p>
               </q>
               <p>By the Statute 2 &amp; 3 <hi>Ph.</hi> &amp; <hi>Ma. Ch.</hi> 9. <q>All Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences to keep Houſes or Places of unlawful Games ſhall be void.</q> Before this Statute ſeveral
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49981:12"/>
Perſons uſed to obtain Placards, or Licences to keep common Gaming; ſo that by this Statute all ſuch Licences are made void.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> An Account of ſome Texts of Scripture, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſad Conſequences and Effects that attend the cuſtomary, ſinful and profane practice of profuſe Quaffing and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SUCH Perſons as neither the fear of the Law, reſpect to their own Credit, nor love to their Families, will reclaim or deter from their obſtinate and preſumptuous, ſinful Progreſs in their profane Courſes of cuſtomary, expenſive, and profuſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Tipling, and inordinate Drinking, upon the peruſal of theſe ſeveral Scripture-ſentences following, may I hope be thereby induced and excited to follow a more frugal, vertuous and godly courſe of Living, and to abandon the charming <hi>Delilah</hi>of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſinful Vice.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>And they ſhall ſay unto the Elders of his City, This our Son is ſtubborn and rebellions, he will not obey our Voice, he is a Glutton and a Drunkard. And all the men of his City ſhall ſtone him with ſtones that he die; ſo ſhalt thou put evil away from among you, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall hear and fear. <bibl>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 20, 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Wine is a Mocker, ſtrong drink is raging; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is deceived thereby is not wiſe. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 1.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49981:12"/>
                  <q>Be not among Wine-bibbers, amongst riotous eaters of Fleſh. For the Drunkard and the Glutton ſhall come to Poverty, and drowſineſs ſhall clothe a man with Rags. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 20, 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Who hath wo? who hath ſorrow? who hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions? who hath bablings? who hath wounds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe? who hath redneſs of Eyes? They that tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long at the Wine, they that go to ſeek mixt Wine. Look not thou upon the Wine when it is red, when it giveth his colour in the Cup, when it moveth it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. At the laſt it biteth like a Serpent, and ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth like an Adder. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 29, 30, 31, 32.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Wo unto them that riſe up early in the Morning, that they may follow ſtrong Drink, that continue until Night, till Wine inflame them. And the Harp and the Viol, the Tabret and Pipe, and Wine are in their Feaſts: but they regard not the Work of the Lord, neither conſider the Operation of his Hands. <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 11, 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Wo unto them that are mighty to drink Wine, and Men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong Drink. <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 22.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Wo to the Crown of Pride, to the Drunkards of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> whoſe glorious Beauty is a fading Flower, which are on the Head of the fat Vallies of them that are overcome with Wine. Behold, the Lord hath a mighty and ſtrong One, which as a Tempeſt of Hail, and a deſtroying Storm, as a flood of mighty Waters overflowing, ſhall caſt down to the Earth with the Hand. The Crown of Pride, the Drunkards of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> ſhall be troden under feet. <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. 1, 2, 3.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Come ye, ſay they, I will fetch Wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong Drink; and to morrow ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49981:13"/>
be as this day, and much more abundant. <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Then ſaid the Lord unto me, Go yet, love a Woman (beloved of her friend, yet an Adultereſs) accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Love of the Lord toward the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who look to other Gods, and love Flagons of Wine. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3. 1.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whoredom and Wine, and new Wine take away the Heart. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Awake, ye Drunkards, and weep and howl all ye drinkers of Wine, becauſe of the new Wine, for it is cut off from your Mouth. <bibl>
                        <hi>Joel</hi> 1. 5.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Wo to them that are at eaſe in <hi>Zion;</hi> that chaunt to the ſound of the Viol, and invent to themſelves Inſtruments of Muſick, like <hi>David:</hi> That drink Wine in Bowls, and anoint themſelves with the chief Ointments; but they are not grieved for the Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Amos 6. 1, 5, 6.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For while they be folden together as Thorns, and while they are drunken as Drunkards, they ſhall be devoured as Stubble fully dry. <bibl>
                        <hi>Nahum</hi> 1. 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Wo unto him that giveth his Neighbour Drink, and putteſt thy Bottle to him, and makeſt him drunken alſo, that thou mayſt look on their Nakedneſs. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakkuk</hi> 2. 15.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>How exceeding ſtrong is Wine! it cauſeth all Men to err that drink it: And when they are in their Cups, they forget their Love both to Friends and Brethren, and a little after draw out Swords. <bibl>1 <hi>Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r.</hi> 3. 18, 22.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Do that to no Man which thou hateſt: Drink not Wine to make thee drunken: neither let Drunkenneſs go with thee in thy Journey. <bibl>
                        <hi>Tob.</hi> 4. 15.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>A drunken Woman and a gadder abroad, cauſeth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49981:13"/>
great Anger, and ſhe will not cover her own ſhame. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 26. 8.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Shew not thy Valiantneſs in Wine, for Wine hath deſtroy'd many. Wine drunken with exceſs, maketh bitterneſs of Mind, with brawling and quarrelling. Drunkenneſs increaſeth the Rage of a Fool, till he offend; it diminiſheth Strength, and maketh Wounds. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 31. 25, 29, 30.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Therefore thou ſhalt ſay unto them, Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Drink ye, and be drunken, and ſpue and fall, and riſe no more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Sword which I will ſend among you. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 27.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But and if that evil Servant ſhall ſay in his Heart, My Lord delayeth his coming, and ſhall begin to ſmite his fellow-Servants, and to eat and drink with the drunken: The Lord of that Servant ſhall come in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour that he is not aware of: And ſhall cut him aſunder, and appoint him his Portion with the Hypocrites: there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth. <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 48, 49, 50, 51.</bibl> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 45, 46.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And take heed to your ſelves, left at any time your Hearts be over-charged with Surfeiting and Drunkenneſs, and Cares of this Life, and ſo that day come upon you unawares. <bibl>
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 34.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Let us walk honeſtly as in the day, not in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strife and Envying: But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make no Proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the Luſts thereof. <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 13, 14.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But now I have written unto you, not to keep company, if any Man that is called a Brother be a Fornicator, or Covetous, or an Idolater, or a Railer,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49981:14"/>
or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner; with ſuch an one, no not to eat. <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Know ye not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? Be not deceived; neither Fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, nor abuſers of themſelves with Mankind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Revilers, nor Extortioners ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God. <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Now the Works of the Fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe, Adultery, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs, Idolatry, Witchcraft, Hatred, Variance, Emulation, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Hereſies, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyings, Murders, Drunkenneſs, Revellings, and ſuch like: of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God. <bibl>
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 19, 20, 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And be not drunken with Wine, wherein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; but be filled with the Spirit. <bibl>
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Therefore let us not ſleep as do others: but let us watch and be ſober. For they that ſleep, ſleep in the night; and they that be drunken, are drunken in the night. 1 <bibl>
                        <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 6, 7.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems in the times of the Apoſtles, that Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards were poſſeſſed with ſome kind of Dread and Fear that attended the Guilt of their profligate and vicious Lives, or elſe they were aſham'd that their ſinful Debaucheries ſhould be publickly known, or apparently ſeen: For St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians, <hi>They that be drunken, are drunken in the Night.</hi> But it appears otherwiſe now in our days and time. For,</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49981:14"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tempora mutantur, &amp; nos mutamur in illis.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Both Times and Men are chang'd, and alter'd quite.</l>
                     <l>Drunkards are drunk by Day as well as Night.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>For theſe Champions of <hi>Bacchus</hi> are neither poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd with Fear, nor are they aſham'd even at Noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to expoſe themſelves publickly and openly to the view of all People, in their debauched, profane, loathſom, abominable, ſinful Diſguiſes.</p>
               <p>Leſt therefore neither Law nor Goſpel can ſtop ſuch habituated and deſperate Drunkards in the career of their profuſe and ſinful drunken Careſſes, I ſhall in the next Chapter acquaint them with ſeveral ſignal and exemplary Judgments of God's ſevere Juſtice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon obſtinate, deſperate, preſumptuous, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, cuſtomary, profane, ſinful Drunkards, in hopes that their ſerious Peruſal and Conſideration thereof may have ſome influence upon them, and prove a means to ſeaſon them with ſome conſiderable meaſures of Religion and Piety.</p>
               <p>And I hope they will take notice of that excellent ſaying of the Orator, <hi>Lege hiſtoriam</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ne ſias hiſtoria</hi>; That they will read the following Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories with ſuch deliberation, and apply them ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, that they may thereby avert the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Almighty, and prevent the like Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from falling upon their Heads; leſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Hiſtory to after Ages themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49981:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of ſeveral exemplary Judgments, both Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Modern, Foreign and Domeſtick, of God's ſevere Juſtice inflicted upon cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, preſumptuous, and profane ſinful Drunkards.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>DRunkenneſs is a Vice not fit to be named (ſays a learned Divine) much leſs to be practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians; nay, we are forbid not ſo much as to look upon the Wine when it is red, when it ſparkles in the Cup; or to riſe up early in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to follow drink that is ſtrong, as appears by the places of Scripture beforecited in the laſt preceding Chapter.</p>
               <p>And we read that <hi>Pitticus</hi> the Mitelenian Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and one of the ſeven wiſe men of <hi>Greece,</hi> made a Law, that whoſoever committed a Crime when he was drunk, ſhould be puniſhed double, both for the Offence committed, and alſo for being drunk. And <hi>Solon</hi> another of the ſeven wiſe men of <hi>Greece,</hi> and the famous Law-giver to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> ordained, that if any Prince were taken drunk, he ſhould be put to death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noah</hi> that Holy Patriarch drinking too much Wine, not only diſcovered his own ſhame, but alſo was the occaſion of the cruel Curſe which the Lord ſent upon the Poſterity of <hi>Cham,</hi> which even to this day lieth hard upon them.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Lot</hi> though he hated the Sin of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49981:15"/>
eſcaped the Puniſhment thereof; yet being overcome with the Wine of the Mountains, he committed Inceſt with his own Daughters, and made a new <hi>Sodom</hi> of his own Family.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Balthaſar</hi> rioting and revelling amongſt his Whores, had the end of his Life and Kingdom denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him by a bodileſs Hand, writing upon the Wall the Lord's Decree.</p>
               <p>And whilſt <hi>Holofernes</hi> beſotted his ſences with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Wine, and good Chear, <hi>Judith</hi> found means to cut off his Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, having invited many of his Favourites and Captains to a Supper, propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Crown in reward to him that ſhould drink moſt; ſo one in the Company ſwallowed up four Steans of Wine, being in value worth ſix hundred Crowns, and ſo won the Prize, but loſt a greater Prize, <hi>(viz.</hi> his Life) for he ſurvived not three days after; and one and forty of the reſt that did ſtrive with him for Conqueſt, dyed alſo to bear him Company at his Death, as they had done in the Frolick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> alſo himſelf was ſo addicted to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of drinking Wine, and was oft-times ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered therewith, that ſometimes he kill'd his Friends at the Table in his drunken fits, whom in ſobriety he loved deareſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyrillus</hi> a Citizen of <hi>Hippon,</hi> had a drunken Son, who in the midſt of his Drunkenneſs, kill'd his own Mother great with Child, and his Father alſo that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to reſtrain his drunken Fury; and would have raviſhed his Siſter, had ſhe not ſtrugled ſore and made her eſcape, not without many wounds.</p>
               <p>Three not far from <hi>Huntington,</hi> to my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg (ſaith my Author) being overcharged with Drink,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49981:16"/>
periſhed by Drowning; when being not able to rule their Horſes, they were carried by them into the main Stream, from whence they never came out again a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, but left behind them viſible marks of God's Juſtice, for the Terror and Example of others.</p>
               <p>Upon the Coaſts of <hi>Bohemia, Anno</hi> 1551. five drunken men quaffing together, with horrible Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, profaned the Name of God; and the Picture of the Devil being painted on the Wall, they carouſed Healths to him, to which the Devil anſwered immediately: and the next Morning all five were found dead, their Necks being broken, and ſqueez'd to pieces as though a Wheel had gone over them, Blood running out of their Mouths, Noſtrils, and Ears, to the great Aſtoniſhment of the Beholders.</p>
               <p>An Alewife in <hi>Keſgrave</hi> near <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> who would needs force three Serving-men (that had been drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her Houſe, and were taking their leaves) to ſtay and drink the three Outs before they went, that is, Wit out of the Head, Money out of the Purſe, and Ale out of the Barrel; as ſhe was coming towards them, with the Pot in her hand, was ſuddenly taken ſpeechleſs, and ſick, and her Tongue ſwoln in her Head, and never recovered her Speech, but di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the third day after.</p>
               <p>Two Servants of a Brewer in <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> drinking for the Rump of a Turkey, and ſtrugling in their Drink for it, fell into a ſcalding Caldron backwards, whereof one died preſently, and the other lingringly and painfully, ſince my coming (ſays Mr. <hi>Ward)</hi> to <hi>Ipſwich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Man coming home drunk, would needs go and ſwim in the Mill-pond; his Wife and Servants know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he could not ſwim, perſwaded him, and once got
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49981:16"/>
him out of the Water, but he going in again, was drowned in the Pond.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Barnwel</hi> near <hi>Cambridg,</hi> a luſty young man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the ſign of the <hi>Plough,</hi> with two of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and one Woman in their Company, agreed to drink up a Barrel of ſtrong Beer; and drinking up the ſame, three of them died within four and twenty Hours, and the fourth hardly eſcaped after great Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>A Butcher in <hi>Haſlingfield,</hi> hearing the Miniſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt Drunkenneſs, being at his Cups in the Alehouſe, fell a ſcoffing at the Miniſter and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and as he was drinking, the Drink, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Cup, got into his Throat and ſtuck ſo there, that he could neither get it up nor down, but was choaked therewith preſently.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Tillingham</hi> in <hi>Dengy</hi> Hundred in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Three young men meeting to drink ſtrong Waters, fell by degrees to half Pints, and one of them fell down dead in the Room; and the other two prevented by Company coming in, eſcaped not without much Sickneſs.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Bungy</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> three coming out of an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in a dark Evening, ſwore they thought it was not darker in Hell it ſelf: one of them fell off the Bridg into the Water and was drowned, the ſecond fell off his Horſe, and the third ſleeping on the Ground by the River ſide was frozen to Death.</p>
               <p>A Bailiff of <hi>Hedley,</hi> being drunk upon the Lord's Day at <hi>Melford,</hi> would needs get upon his Mare to ride through the Street, affirming (as the report goes, ſays my Author) that his Mare would carry him to the Devil; and his Mare caſting him off broke his neck.</p>
               <p>Company drinking in an Alehouſe at <hi>Harwich</hi> in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49981:17"/>
the Night, over againſt one Mr. <hi>Ruſſels</hi> Mayor of the Town, was by him once or twice deſired to depart; and at length coming down, he took one of them, making as if he would carry him to Priſon; who drawing his Knife, fled from him, and was three days after taken out of the Sea with the Knife in his hand.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Tenby</hi> in <hi>Pembrokſhire,</hi> a Drunkard being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive drunk, broke himſelf all to pieces, from an high and ſteep Rock, in a moſt fearful manner; and yet the occaſion and Circumſtances of his fall ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, as I (ſays my Author) think not fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, leſt in ſo ſerious a Judgment, I ſhould move laughter to the Reader.</p>
               <p>A Glaſier in <hi>Chancery-lane</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> fell to a common courſe of Drinking, and being admoniſhed by his Wife, and many of his Friends, to leave off his ſinful Courſe; yet he preſuming much of God's Mercy, continued in his ſinful practiſe, till upon a time having overcharged his Stomach with Drink, he fell a vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, broke a Vein, lay two days in extream pain of Body, and ſorrow of Mind, till in the end recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little Comfort, he died.</p>
               <p>Four ſundry inſtances of Drunkards, wallowing and tumbling in their Drink, and ſlain by Carts, I (ſays my Author) forbear to mention, becauſe ſuch Examples are ſo common and ordinary.</p>
               <p>A Yeoman's Son in <hi>Northamtonſhire,</hi> being drunk at <hi>Wellingborough</hi> on a Market day, would needs ride his Horſe in bravery over the Ploughed Lands, ſo fell from his Horſe and broke his Neck.</p>
               <p>A Knight notoriouſly given to drink, carrying ſome Pales of Drink into the open Fields to make People drunk withal, being upon a time drinking with Company, a Woman comes in, delivering him
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49981:17"/>
a Ring with this Poſy in it, <hi>Drink and Die,</hi> ſaying to him, this is for you, which he took and wore, and within a Week after came to his end by drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>One of <hi>Ayleſham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> a notorious Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, was drowned in a ſhallow Brook of Water, with his Horſe. And one to my own knowledg in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> being drunk, as he was going home, fell down upon his Face into a very ſmall running Water, and was drowned there, though the back ſide of his Head was all dry, and not covered with the Water.</p>
               <p>Two examples (ſays Mr. <hi>Ward)</hi> have I known of Children that murdered their own Mothers in drink, and one notorious Drunkard that attempted to kill his Father; of which being prevented, he fired his Barn, and was afterwards executed.</p>
               <p>A young Fellow of <hi>North-Allerton</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> being Drunk, and having ſome reproof given him by his Mother, he murdered her in her own Houſe, upon a <hi>Good-Friday;</hi> ſhe having received the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that day, and being but come from the Church a little before.</p>
               <p>At a Tavern in <hi>Breadſtreet</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> certain Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen drinking Healths to their Lords, on whom they had Dependance, one deſperate Wretch ſteps to the Tables end, lays hold of a Pottle Pot of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Sack; ſwears a deep Oath, What! will none drink a Health to my noble Lord and Maſter? and ſo ſetting the Pottle Pot to his head, drank it off to the Bottom, but was not able to riſe up, or to ſpeak when he had done, but fell into a deep ſnoaring Sleep; and being removed, laid aſide, and covered by one of the Servants in the Houſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49981:18"/>
the time of his waking, was within the ſpace of two hours irrecoverably dead.</p>
               <p>A man in <hi>Suffolk</hi> overtaken with Wine, (tho never in all his Life before, as he himſelf ſaid a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Death, and others that knew him ſaid the ſame) vet going down a pair of Stairs, againſt the perſwaſion of a Woman (ſitting by him in his Chamber) he fell, and was ſo dangerouſly hurt, that he died ſoon after, not being able to ſpeak from the time of his Fall to his Death. I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, ſays my Author, to name the parties thus puniſhed for their Kindreds ſakes, yet living, ſays he.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Dengy</hi> Hundred near <hi>Maldon,</hi> there fell out an extraordinary Judgment upon five or ſix that plotted a ſolemn Drinking at one of their Houſes, laid in Beer for the purpoſe; drunk Healths in a ſtrange manner, and all died thereof within a few Weeks after, ſome ſooner, and ſome later.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1618, one <hi>Thomas Alred</hi> of <hi>Godman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> in <hi>Huntingdonſhire,</hi> Butcher, an accuſtomed Drunkard, being entreated by a Neighbour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitch a load of Hay; and being at that very time in drink, leting his Pitchfork ſlip out of his hand, and ſtooping to take it up again, ſlipped from the Cart with his head downwards; his Fork ſtanding upright with the Tines, he fell directly upon them, which at once run him into the Breaſt, and ſtruck his Heart ſo, that he died ſuddenly.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>July</hi> 1628. one <hi>John Vintner</hi> of <hi>Godman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> Gardiner, a known Drunkard, and one that would profanely (eſpecially in his drink) ſcoff at Religion, and abuſe good men, fell from the top
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49981:18"/>
of a Pear-Tree, and brake his Neck, and ſo died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Manlius</hi> in his common Places, gives a Relation of three abominable Drunkards, who drank ſo long till one of them fell down ſtark dead; and yet the other two nothing terrified with ſuch a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful example of divine Vengeance, proceeded on ſtill in their vain preſumptuous drinking, and poured the dead mans part into him, as he lay by them: So that the Text in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. might well be applied to them; <hi>They regard not the work of the Lord, neither conſider the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> tells of one <hi>Theotimus,</hi> that being told by his Phyſicians, that much Quaffing would make him blind; <hi>Vale Lumen Amicum,</hi> ſaid he:
<q>
                     <l>Farewel dear Eyes, if ye can bear no Wine,</l>
                     <l>Then ye no Eyes ſhall henceforth be of mine.</l>
                  </q>
So that he would rather loſe his Sight than his Sin, his Soul than his Luſt. And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> brings in a Drunkard ſaying, <hi>Malle ſe vitam quam vinum eripi,</hi> he had rather loſe his Life than his Wine.</p>
               <p>We are told by a credible Author, That about eight Perſons that were Citizens, and Citizens Sons, in the Country of <hi>Swaben,</hi> meeting together at a Tavern on a Sabbath-day morning, proceeded to that height, that they drank themſelves drunk, and then began to blaſpheme God, and ſcoff at the Vintner, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed them to leave drinking, and go to Church, and hear the Word of God preached; at which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they did not only continue to mock, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued on their drinking; but on a ſudden the Devil coming in among them, in a Gentlemans Habit, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49981:19"/>
drinking to them, ſet their Mouths in ſuch a Fire, that theſe Drunkards not only became amazed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, but alſo after a miſerable manner were all ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to death.</p>
               <p>A Soldier in <hi>Salisbury,</hi> in the midſt of his Health-drinking and Carouſing in a Tavern, drank a Health to the Devil, ſaying, that if the Devil would not come and pledg him, he would not believe that there was either God or Devil; whereupon his Companions being ſtrucken with Horror, haſted out of the Room: and preſently after hearing an hideous noiſe, and ſmelling a ſtinking Savour, the Vintner went up into the Chamber, and coming in, he miſſed his Gueſt, and found the Window broken, the Iron Bar in it bowed, and all Blood, but the man was never heard of afterwards.</p>
               <p>A Vintner that accuſtomed himſelf to Swearing and Drunkenneſs, as he was upon a Lords-day ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his Door, with a Pot in his Hand, to invite in Gueſts, there carne ſuddenly ſuch a violent Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, as carried him up into the Air, after which he was never more ſeen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zeno</hi> the Emperor was ſuch a Drunkard, that he would often lie as one dead for many hours; ſo that he grew not only odious to all People, but even to his own Wife, who upon a time finding him in that caſe, cauſed him to be laid in a Tomb with a great Stone upon the top of it, whereby he was miſerably pined to death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maginus</hi> reports, of <hi>Fliolmus</hi> King of <hi>Goths,</hi> that he was by his drunken Servants thrown headlong into a Veſſel of Ale, and therein was drowned.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49981:19"/>
In <hi>Gloceſterſhire,</hi> an horrid Patricide was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by an ungracious Son being drunk, upon his Father whom he deſperately ſlew.</p>
               <p>The like unnatural Villany was committed by one <hi>Purchas</hi> an <hi>Eſſex</hi> Monſter, upon the Body of his Mother, whom he likewiſe ſlew.</p>
               <p>In the Pariſh of <hi>Caſtle-Terra,</hi> in the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> a Gentleman when he met with jovial Company, uſed to drink Healths, and throw the Glaſſes againſt the Walls; he delighted alſo to contradict what Miniſters delivered in their Sermons; and having heard one preach of the Benefits and Trial of a juſtifying Faith, after Sermon he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the Preacher, whether he could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move Mountains; if I could ſee you do that, then (ſaid he) I would believe you had Faith, otherwiſe not; for does not the Goſpel ſay, <hi>If a Man have Faith but as a Grain of Muſtard ſeed, he ſhall ſay to Mountains, be removed hence, and it ſhall be done?</hi> But at length this Gentleman was ſtrucken with the Small-pox, which got into his Throat in ſuch manner, that he could not ſwallow nor let down a little Beer, to cool his exceſſive internal Heat; wherewith being ſore tormented, he broke out into theſe Expreſſions to an honeſt man that ſtood by, O <hi>Thomas,</hi> would I could now receive one of thoſe Glaſs-fulls of Drink, which former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I have thrown againſt the Wall in a Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: and afterwards when he ſaw there was no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but die he muſt, he ſaid again, O that I now had Faith like a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed: and a little after he deceaſed in the fifty ſeventh year of his Age.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49981:20"/>
We read of a Drunkard (ſays Mr. <hi>Clark)</hi> who in the midſt of his Cups, ſold his Soul to the Devil for a Tankard of Wine, and the Devil forthwith had his Bargain.</p>
               <p>A certain young man that had devoted himſelf to a pious and retired courſe of Life, was much aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted by the Devil by ſundry Temptations, and preſſed to make choice of one of theſe three Sins, once to be drunk, or to lie with his Neighbours Wife, or to kill his Neighbour; and the Temptation ſo far prevailed, that at laſt he choſe the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> once to be drunk, as deeming it the leaſt Sin; but when the Devil had drawn him to that, at the ſame time both the other Sins were committed by him: For as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves, <hi>Ad univerſa vel crudelitatis vel turpitudinis facinora perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranda facilis invenitur via, cui nulla ſobriæ men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ratio, ſed ebrietas dominatur.</hi> When Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs gets rule and dominion over a man, he is then eaſily drawn to commit any ſort of Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany: ſo when the young man was gotten drunk, he then did not ſcruple to lie with his Neighbour's Wife, and to kill his Neighbour too.</p>
               <p>A certain Drunkard whom I (ſays a godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter) knew very well, when he was in drink, quarrelled with his fellow-Servant, and after a few words knock'd him down with his Flail, and kill'd him at one blow; yet when he came to his Trial, by the help of his Friends he made a ſhift to eſcape the Halter, and came home again, and there he uſed to ſwear and curſe, and drink at as high a rate as ever; but at laſt when he was in the ſame Yard, where he committed the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Murder, he fell down dead in a moment: and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49981:20"/>
I was (ſaith the ſame Miniſter) one of the firſt that ſaw him.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us a Story for a certain Truth: There is in <hi>London</hi> (ſaith he) an underſtanding ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber pious man, oft one of my Hearers, who hath an elder Brother, a Gentleman of conſiderable Rank, who having formerly ſeemed pious, of late years doth oft fall into the Sin of Drunkenneſs; he oft lodgeth long together here, in this his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe, and whenever he is drunk, and hath ſlept himſelf ſober, ſomething knocks at his Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as if one knocked on the Wainſcot; when they remove the Bed, it followeth him; beſides loud noiſes in other parts where he is, that all the Houſe heareth. They have oft watch'd, and kept his Hands, leſt he ſhould do it himſelf; and his Brother has often told me, and brought his Wife (a diſcreet Woman) to atteſt it, who aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth moreover that ſhe watching him, has ſeen his Shoes under the Bed taken up, and nothing touch them; they brought to me the man himſelf, and when we asked him how he dared to ſin after ſuch a warning, he had no excuſe: but being a perſon of Quality, for ſome ſpecial reaſon, I (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter)</hi> muſt not name him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nathaniel Butler</hi> was firſt addicted to Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, Gaming, Purloining, and Fornication, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he committed that murder upon his Friend <hi>John Knight</hi> in <hi>Milk-ſtreet, London,</hi> 1657. for which he was afterwards condemned to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and executed.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>William Rogers</hi> an Apothecary in <hi>Crane-brook</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> exceedingly much given to Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Sabbath-breaking, tho a young man of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49981:21"/>
a pleaſing ſweet Temper, was often admoniſhed and perſwaded by Mr. <hi>Robert Abbot</hi> Miniſter of the place to come to Church, but had often promiſed and failed. But one Lord's-day in the morning, when he ſaid he was ready to come, he was taken ſick and betook him to his Bed, but it proving on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Ague, next morning he betook him to his old courſe again; next Week after the Meſſenger of Death came in earneſt, Mr. <hi>Abbot</hi> addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to him in his Chamber, with theſe words; O how often have you deceived God, your own Soul, and me, and what is now to be done? I fear you will die, and then what will become of you! his Sickneſs prevailed, and there was too great a Fire kindled in his Breaſt to be ſmothered, it burned in his own Soul, and it lightned from his Heart and Lips into the Ears and Hearts of thoſe about him: one while he cries out of his Sins, ſaying, I have been a fearful Drunkard, pouring in one draught after another, till one draught could not keep down another, I now would be glad if I could take the leaſt of God's Creatures which I have abuſed; and have neglected my Patients which have put their Lives into my hands; and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls have I thus murdered? I have wilfully neglected God's Houſe, Service and Worſhip; and tho I purpoſed to go, God ſtrikes me thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of my promiſe comes, becauſe I am unworthy to come amongſt God's People. Again, another while he falls to wiſhing, O that I might burn a long time in that Fire, (pointing to the Fire before him) ſo I might not burn in Hell; O that God would grant me but one year, or a month, that the World might ſee with what an
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49981:21"/>
Heart I have promiſed to God amendment! O that God would try me a little, but I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy. Another while to his Companions—Beware by me to forſake your wicked ways, leſt you go to Hell as I muſt do; calls his young Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, tells him that he had been a wicked Maſter to him, But be warn'd by me, ſays he, you have a Friend that has an Iron Furnace which burns hot and long; but if you give your ſelf to my Sins, you ſhall be burned in the furnace of Hell, an hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Furnace, millions of millions of Ages. The Miniſter propounding the Goſpel-promiſes of the largeſt ſize, he cri'd, it is too late, I muſt be burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Hell: he preſſed him with Tears not to caſt away his Soul, <hi>for Chriſt died,</hi> &amp;c. he anſwered, he caſt off Chriſt, and therefore muſt go to Hell; in ſhort, at laſt in idleneſs of thoughts and talk he ended his miſerable Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1576. <hi>Tir-Owen,</hi> the Iriſh Rebel in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, was ſuch a Drunkard, that when his Body was immoderately inflamed with drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrong Drink and Uſquebath, he uſed many times (as Mr. <hi>Camden</hi> reports) to be ſet in the Earth up to the Chin to cool himſelf.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman whom I knew, having been at a Fair at <hi>North-Allerton</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> (a Town fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for ſtrong Ale) and there having overcharged himſelf with that Liquor; as he was riding home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, putting his Horſe into a galloping poſture, the Horſe being in great heart and very mettl'd, and he not in a condition to guide him, having gotten about a mile from the Town, the Horſe threw the Gentleman in the open High-way, and kill'd him with the Fall; for he died preſently.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49981:22"/>
Another Perſon with whom I had been long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, (he being Barliff to the Lords of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-Town, where I kept their Courts ſeveral years) being full of ſtrong Drink, and not able to govern his Horſe, was in like manner ſlain with a fall from his Horſe.</p>
               <p>And one who lived in the ſame Town where I lived, having gotten too large a quantity of ſtrong Drink, and riding his Horſe into a River to paſs over it, the Water at that time being very high, and ſcarce paſſable, and he not keeping the Horſes head up againſt the current of the Water, when he came into the main Stream, being driven down the River, after a little while he parted from his Horſe and was drowned.</p>
               <p>And another of my Acquaintance, being invited by a Gentleman to the Tavern, and there drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too freely; at his going homewards from the Tavern, on the back-ſide of the Town, coming to enter into his own Yard, he fell from off a little Bridg at the end of the Yard, with his Head downwards into a Ditch; and tho the Ditch were dry without any Water in it, and that he was miſſed, and found in a very ſhort time, yet he was found dead, for the weight of his Body had choaked him.</p>
               <p>A man being riding in the ſame Company that I was in, and being very full of ſtrong Liquor, and clapping his Spurs to the Horſes ſides, the Horſe run into a Ditch or Gutter with the man on his back; and riding along in the Gutter, a Tree in the Hedg over hanging the ſame, the Horſe run the man's Head againſt the Tree, and beat out his Brains, and he fell down dead and never ſpoke one word;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49981:22"/>
of this ſad Accident I was an Eye-witneſs, and ſee the man's Brains lying on the Ground.</p>
               <p>And one who was a cuſtomary, proſane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and a great Drinker, being gotten drunk at <hi>North-Allerton</hi> aforeſaid, and deſiring one of his Neighbours to let him ride home behind him; when they came near the Town where the Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard dwelt, he deſired to alight from behind his Neighbour to eaſe himſelf; and ſo getting down, his Neighbour rid along the Street; and ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany coming not long after, found the man dead, lying in the Street with his Breeches about his Feet, in an unſeemly and naſty manner.</p>
               <p>A Maſon who loved ſtrong Drink too well, and was frequently drunk, one time lying down upon the ground to ſober himſelf when he was drunk, he fell into a long Sleep, for he never awaked again, but was there found dead.</p>
               <p>A Farmer who lived in <hi>Cleaveland</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> in the ſame Conſtablery where I have a ſmall Eſtate, going with other of his Neighbours to pay his Tythe Rent to the Impropriator, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a jovial boon, free man, was very liberal, and beſtow'd great ſtore of ſtrong Ale on them. And this man having drunk too freely, had it ſeems got more than he was able to bear; for when he was got very near his own Houſe, at his coming home, when he alighted from his Horſe, it being in the Night, and dark, and he not able to guide himſelf, he ſtagge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed into a Pond cloſe by the Houſe, and not able to get out of it, was in the Morning found ſtanding in the Pond, with his Back againſt the bank of the Pond, and up to the Knees in Water, and there ſtarv'd to death. All
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49981:23"/>
theſe eight laſt mentioned exemplary Judgments have fall'n within the compaſs of my own certain knowledg.</p>
               <p>Drunkenneſs is a flattering Evil, a ſweet Poiſon, a cunning <hi>Circe</hi> that beſots the Soul, and deſtroys the Body; <hi>Dolores gignit in capite, in ſtomacho, in toto corpore acerrimos.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Dolours and grievous Pains, by Drunkenneſs,</l>
                  <l>The Head, the Stomach, and whole man poſſeſs.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>At laſt</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves) <hi>it bites like a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſtings like an Adder.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A Compendium of the Laws made againſt profane, idle, cuſtomary Swearing and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TIpling and exceſſive Drinking having obtain'd a kind and favourable Reception, and in a manner a general approbation within this Realm, as appears by the ſeveral Acts of Parliament (men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before in the firſt Chapter hereof) made for the reſtraining this exorbitant ſinful Vice; the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their Frolicks, and extravagant Cups, were apt and prone to fly out (one profaneneſs uſhering in another) into ſinful profane, deſperate Swearing and Curſing, which by little and little began to be ſo very common and practicable, that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49981:23"/>
of 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. taking notice thereof, and knowing that profane Swearing and Curſing is forbidden by the Word of God, they thereupon made an Act for the reſtraining the growth of this catching Sin.</p>
               <p>For by the Statute of 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 20. it is Enacted,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That no Perſon or Perſons ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanely Swear or Curſe; and that if any Perſon or Perſons ſhall offend herein, either in the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any Juſtice of the Peace of the County, or any Mayor, Juſtice of the Peace, Bailiff, or Head Officer of any City, or Town Corporate, where ſuch offence is or ſhall be committed, or ſhall be convicted by the Oaths of two Witneſſes, or by Confeſſion of the party, before any ſuch Juſtice of the Peace of the County, or Head Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, or Juſtice of the Peace in the City, or Town-Corporate, where ſuch offence is or ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, (which Oath they have power to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter) That then every ſuch Offender ſhall for every time ſo offending, forfeit and pay to the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh, where the offence is or ſhall be committed, the ſum of twelve Pence, to be levied by the Conſtable, Church-wardens, and overſeers of the Poor of that Pariſh, by Warrant from ſuch Juſtice of the Peace, or head Officer, by Diſtreſs, and ſale of the Offenders Goods, rendring to the party the Overplus: and in default of ſuch Diſtreſs, the Offender, if he or ſhe be above the age of twelve Years, ſhall by Warrant from ſuch Juſtice of the Peace, or Head Officer, be ſet in the Stocks three hours; but if the Offender be under that Age, and ſhall not forthwith pay the ſame ſum of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49981:24"/>
twelve Pence, then he or ſhe by ſuch Warrant as aforeſaid, ſhall be whip'd by the Conſtable, or by the Parent or Maſter in his preſence.</p>
                  <p>And if ſuch Offender ſhall commence any Suit at Law, againſt any Officer, or other, for ſuch diſtraining, ſale of Goods, whipping, or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Stocks, the Defendant, or Defendants, may plead the general Iſſue, and give the ſpecial matter in evidence to the Jury at the Trial; and if it be found againſt the Plaintiff, or Plaintiffs, or they are Nonſuited, then the Defendant, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants ſhall be allowed good Coſts to be taxed by the Court.</p>
                  <p>The Offence ſhall be complained of, and proved as aboveſaid, within twenty days after the Offence committed.</p>
                  <p>And it is Enacted, That this Act ſhall be read in every Pariſh-Church by the Miniſter thereof, upon the Sunday after Evening-Prayer, twice in the Year.</p>
               </q>
               <p>There being no Penalty inflicted upon Miniſters by this Statute of the 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. for the not reading thereof, it was therefore in moſt Churches very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and in ſome Churches never read; and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a long time ſince the making of this Law, and the Penalty appointed thereby to be paid by the Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers very ſmall, and proof by two witneſſes troubleſom, it was therefore very ſeldom put in execution. So for the more effectual diſcouragement, and reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this ſpreading and catching, profane Vice, another Act of Parliament has been made in the ſixth and ſeventh years of his preſent Majeſties reign, King <hi>William</hi> the third, ſomething more ſevere, as appears by the Tenure thereof, hereafter following.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:49981:24"/>
By the Statute of the 6 &amp; 7 <hi>Gul.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2. it is Enacted,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That if any Perſon or Perſons ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely Swear or Curſe in the preſence and hearing of any Juſtice of Peace of the County, Riding, or Diviſion, or of the Mayor or other Head Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, or Juſtice of Peace for any City, or Town-Corporate, or by the Confeſſion of the party of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending before any ſuch Magiſtrate where the ſaid Offence ſhall be committed; that then for every ſuch Offence, the party ſo offending, if a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, Day-labourer, common Soldier, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sea-man, ſhall forfeit and pay to the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh where ſuch offence is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted one Shilling, and every other Perſon two Shillings; and in caſe any of the Perſons aforeſaid, ſhall after Conviction offend a ſecond time, ſuch Perſon ſhall forfeit and pay double; and if a third time, treble the ſum reſpectively by him or her to be paid for the firſt Offence.</p>
                  <p>And upon neglect, or refuſal of paiment of the ſaid Forfeiture, any Juſtice of Peace of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Riding, or Diviſion, or Mayor, or other Head Officer, or Juſtice of Peace, for any City, or Town-Corporate, where the Offence is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſhall have Authority, and are required to ſend his Warrant to the Conſtable, Tything-man, Church-warden, or Overſeer of the Poor of the Pariſh where the Offence is committed, or where the Offender ſhall inhabit, thereby commanding them, or ſome or one of them, to levy by Diſtreſs, and ſale of the Goods of the Offender, or Offenders, the ſum ſo forfeited for the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh as aforeſaid: and for want of Diſtreſs, then every ſuch Offender being above the age of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49981:25"/>
Years, ſhall by ſuch Warrant as aforeſaid, be publickly ſet in the Stocks for the ſpace of one Hour for every ſingle Offence; and for any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Offences, whereof he ſhall be Convicted at one and the ſame time, then two Hours: and if the party offending be under the age of ſixteen years, and ſhall not forthwith pay the ſaid For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, then he or ſhe ſhall by Warrant as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, be whip'd by the Conſtable, or by the Parent, Guardian, or Maſter of ſuch Offender in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Conſtable.</p>
                  <p>And if any Juſtice of Peace, or chief Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate ſhall wilfully, or wittingly omit the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his Duty, in the execution of this Act, he ſhall forfeit the ſum of five Pounds, one moiety to the uſe of the Informer, to be recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Action, Suit, Bill, or Plaint, in any of his Majeſties Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> wherein no Eſſoin, Protection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall be allowed, nor any more than one Imparlance.</p>
                  <p>And if any Action or Suit ſhall be commenc'd, or brought againſt any Juſtice of Peace, Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or other Officer, for any thing done in the purſuance of this Act concerning the ſaid Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, the Defendant in ſuch Action may plead the general Iſſue, and give the ſpecial matter in Evidence; and upon a Verdict for the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, or Non-ſuit of the Plaintiff, or Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, then the Defendant ſhall have treble Coſts.</p>
                  <p>No Perſon to be proſecuted or troubled for any Offence againſt this Statute, unleſs the ſame be proved and proſecuted within ten days next after the Offence committed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49981:25"/>
This Act ſhall be publickly read four ſeveral times in the Year, in all Pariſh Churches, and publick Chappels, by the Parſon, Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of the reſpective Pariſhes or Chappels, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after Morning-Prayer, on four ſeveral Sundays; that is to ſay, the Sunday next after the four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> the nine and twentieth day of <hi>September,</hi> the five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of <hi>December,</hi> and the five and twenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth day of <hi>March;</hi> under the pain of twenty Shillings for every ſuch Omiſſion or Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</p>
                  <p>And the Juſtice of Peace, Mayor, or other Head Officer, ſhall regiſter in a Book, to be kept for that purpoſe, all the Convictions made before him upon this Act, and the time of making thereof, and for what Offence; and ſhall certify the ſame to the next general Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Seſſions of the Peace for the ſaid County or Place, where the Offences are committed, to be there kept upon Record by the reſpective Clerks of the Peace, to be ſeen without Fee or Reward.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Altho ſome Perſons accuſtomed to profane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Curſing in their ordinary diſcourſe and communication, may poſſibly evade the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ordained and appointed by the aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Laws, for ſuch abominable wickedneſs: yet ſuch daring preſumptuous Sinners may be aſſured they cannot (without ſerious and unfeigned Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and an abſolute and total renouncing and forſaking of their Wickedneſs) eſcape the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threatned by Almighty God againſt ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Sins; and that they may not be ignorant
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49981:26"/>
thereof, I ſhall in the next Chapter ſet down ſeveral proofs of Scripture to that purpoſe, in hopes that upon the peruſal and ſerious Conſideration thereof, their Conſciences may be touched with the guilt of their profane debauched Wickedneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Some Texts of Scripture, ſhewing the odiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and danger of profane, cuſtomary Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Curſing.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <q>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his Name in vain. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 7. <bibl>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>He that Curſeth his Father or Mother, ſhall ſurely be put to death. <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 21. 17.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Ruler of thy People. <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 28.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou ſhalt not ſwear by my Name falſly, neither ſhalt thou profane the Name of thy God, I am the Lord. <bibl>
                        <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou ſhalt not curſe the Deaf, nor put a ſtumbling block before the Blind, but ſhalt fear thy God: I am the Lord. <bibl>
                        <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 14.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>He that blaſphemeth the Name of the Lord, he ſhall ſurely be put to death. <bibl>
                        <hi>Levit.</hi> 24. 16.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Every one that curſeth his Father or his Mother, ſhall be ſurely put to death; he hath curſed his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or his Mother, his Blood ſhall be upon him. <bibl>
                        <hi>Lev.</hi> 20. 9.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49981:26"/>
                  <q>Curſed be he that curſeth his Father or his Mother. <bibl>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 16.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly is ſo proud that he careth not for God, neither is God in all his Thoughts. His Mouth is full of Curſing, Deceit, and Fraud; under his Tongue is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and Vanity. <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. 4, 7.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For the ſin of their Mouth, and for the words of their Lips, they ſhall be taken in their Pride, and why? Their Preaching is of Curſing and Lies. <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59. 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Their device is only how to put him out whom God will exalt; their delight is in Lies; they give good words with their Mouth, but curſe with their Heart. <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>His delight was in curſing, and it ſhall happen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; he loved not bleſſing, therefore ſhall it be far from him. He clothed himſelf with Curſing, like as with a Raiment; and it ſhall come into his Bowels like Water, and like Oil into his Bones. <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 16, 17.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The wicked is ſnared by the Tranſgreſſion of his Lips; but the juſt ſhall come out of Trouble. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. 13.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>A wholeſom Tongue is a Tree of Life, but perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein is a breach in Spirit. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>A man's Belly ſhall be ſatisfied with the fruit of his Mouth, and with the increaſe of his Lips ſhall he be filled. Death and Life are in the power of the Tongue, and they that love it ſhall eat the Fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 20, 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whoſo Curſeth his Father or his Mother, his Lamp ſhall be put out in obſcure Darkneſs. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:49981:27"/>
                  <q>Whoſo keepeth his Mouth and his Tongue, keepeth his Soul from Trouble. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 21. 23.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>As the Bird by wandring, as the Swallow by flying, ſo the Curſe cauſeleſs ſhall not come. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 26. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>There is a Generation that curſeth their Father, and doth not bleſs their Mother. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Suffer not thy Mouth to cauſe thy Fleſh to ſin. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 6.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Curſe not the King, no not in thy Thought; and curſe not the rich in thy Bed chamber: For a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the Voice, and that which hath Wings ſhall tell the matter. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For the Land is full of Adulterers; for becauſe of ſwearing the Land mourneth; the pleaſant places of the Wilderneſs are dried up, and their courſe is evil, and their force is not right. Wherefore their way ſhall be unto them as ſlippery ways in the Darkneſs, they ſhall be driven on and fall therein: for I will bring evil upon them, even the year of their Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith the Lord. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 10, 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>By ſwearing and lying, and killing and ſtealing, and committing Adultery, they break out, and Blood toucheth Blood. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For Wiſdom is a loving Spirit, and will not acquit a Blaſphemer of his words; for God is witneſs of his Reins, and a true beholder of his Heart, and a hearer of his Tongue. Therefore he that ſpeaketh unrighteous things cannot be hid, neither ſhall Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance when it puniſheth paſs by him. For inquiſition ſhall be made into the counſels of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and the ſound of his words ſhall come unto the Lord, for the manifeſtation of his wicked Deeds. <bibl>
                        <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 1. 6, 8, 9.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:49981:27"/>
                  <q>The Bleſſing of the Father eſtabliſheth the Houſes of Children, but the Curſe of the Mother rooteth out Foundations. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 3. 9.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Then ſaid he unto me, This is the Curſe that goeth forth over the face of the whole Earth: for every one that ſtealeth ſhall be cut off as on this ſide according to it: and every one that ſweareth ſhall be cut off on that ſide according to it. I will bring it forth, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and it ſhall enter into the Houſe of the Thief, and into the houſe of him that ſweareth falſly by my Name: and it ſhall remain in the midſt of his Houſe, and ſhall conſume it, with the Timber thereof, and the Stones thereof. <bibl>
                        <hi>Zech.</hi> 5. 3, 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Accuſtom not thy Mouth to ſwearing, neither uſe thy ſelf to the naming of the Holy One. A man that uſeth much Swearing, ſhall be filled with Iniquity, and the plague ſhall never depart from his Houſe; if he ſhall offend, his Sin ſhall be upon him; and if he acknowledg not his Sin, he maketh a double Offence; and if he ſwear in vain, he ſhall not be Innocent, but his Houſe ſhall be full of Calamities. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 23. 9. 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But I ſay unto you, Swear not at all, neither by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for it is God's Throne; nor by the Earth, for it is his Foot-ſtool; neither by <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for it is the City of the great King. Neither ſhalt thou ſwear by thy Head, becauſe thou canſt not make one Hair white or black. But let your Communication be, yea, yea, nay, nay; for whatſoever is more than theſe, cometh of evil. <bibl>
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 34, 35, 36, 37.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For God commanded, ſaying, Honour thy Father and thy Mother: and he that Curſeth Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let him die the Death. <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49981:28"/>
                  <q>Their Throat is an open Sepulchre, with their Tongues they have uſed Deceit, the poiſon of Aſps it under their Lips. Whoſe Mouth is full of Curſing and Bitterneſs. Deſtruction and Miſery are in their ways. There is no fear of God before their Eyes. <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 13, 14, 16, 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Let bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking, be put away from you, with all malice. <bibl>
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 31.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Tongue is a Fire, a world of Iniquity; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth the whole Body, and ſetteth on fire the courſe of Nature, and it is ſet on fire of Hell. It is an unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Evil, full of deadly Poiſon. Therewith bleſs we God, and therewith curſe we Men, which are made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſimilitude of God. Out of the ſame Mouth proceedeth Bleſſing and Curſing: my Brethren theſe things ought not ſo to be. <bibl>
                        <hi>James</hi> 3. 6, 8, 9, 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But above all things, my Brethren, ſwear not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Heaven, neither by the Earth, neither by any other Oath; but let your yea be yea, and your nay nay, leſt ye fall into Condemnation. <bibl>
                        <hi>James</hi> 5. 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If any idle, debauched Swearers and Curſers be ſo emboldned in their profane cuſtomary Wickedneſs, as that after the reading or hearing of theſe before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned places of Scripture, they ſhall ſtill dare to proceed and run on in their wilful wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinful Courſes; I ſhall for their further Caution, in this next following Chapter, give them a brief relation of ſeveral ſignal Inſtances of God's ſevere wrath and diſpleaſure againſt ſuch Wickedneſs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by the fearful, terrible, and amazing Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which he hath ſeveral times ſignally inflicted upon ſuch profane ſinful wretches.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49981:28"/>
And I hope upon the peruſal and conſideration of the following exemplary Puniſhments inflicted by God upon others, that all cuſtomary, common Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Curſers will lay it to heart, and that we may find that of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> manifeſted in them; <hi>When thy Judgments are in the Earth, the inhabitants of the World</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>will learn Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> Iſa. 26. 9.</p>
               <p>It was an excellent ſaying of the Poet, <hi>Exemplo alterius qui ſapit, iile ſapit</hi>; He is a wiſe man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that learns Wiſdom by the Example of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and the ſaying is often found true, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis intuentur quid fecerit Jupiter, quam quid decuit Plato.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>More by Example oft reclaimed be,</l>
                  <l>Than are by Precept, and ſmooth Oratry.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of ſeveral ſignal, fearful, and amazing Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God's ſevere Juſtice, inflicted upon cuſtomary profane and preſumptuous Swearers and Curſers.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>EARL <hi>Godwin</hi> juſtifying himſelf before King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Confeſſor, about King <hi>Alfred</hi>'s Death, prayed to God that if he were any way guilty of it, he might never ſwallow down one morſel of Bread; and thereupon by the juſt judgment of God, he was choaked by the firſt Morſel he offered to eat.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49981:29"/>
We find mention made by a good Author, of a wicked wretch in <hi>France,</hi> among the People call'd <hi>Averin,</hi> that forſwearing himſelf in an unjuſt cauſe, had his Tongue ſo tied immediately upon it, that he could not ſpeak, but roar; and ſo continued till by earneſt Prayers and Repentance, the Lord reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him the uſe again of that unruly and ſinful Member.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Narciſſus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a man famous for his Vertues, and ſharpneſs in reproving and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting Vice, was accuſed falſly and maliciouſly of Unchaſtity, by three Sons of <hi>Belial;</hi> The firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely ſaid, If I lie, I pray God I may periſh by Fire. The ſecond, If I ſpeak ought but Truth, I pray God I may be conſumed by ſome filthy and cruel Diſeaſe. The third, If I accuſe him falſly, I pray God I may be deprived of my ſight, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Blind. Thus tho the Honeſty and Chaſtity of <hi>Narciſſus</hi> was ſo well known to all the Faithful, that they believed not what the Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lets atteſted; yet the good Biſhop moved with grief of his Accuſation, and partly with the deſire of quietneſs from worldly Affairs, forſook his Biſhoprick, and lived in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart for many Years. But theſe wicked Wretches by their deaths, witneſſed his Innocence, which by their words they had ſo much impugned; for the firſt had his Houſe ſet on Fire ſo ſuddenly, and in ſuch a violent and extraordinary manner, that he periſhed in the Flames, with all his Family and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny. The ſecond languiſhed away with a tedious infections Diſeaſe, that ſpread his Body all over. The third ſeeing the woful ends of his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, confeſſed all their Villany; and ſadly lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his woful Caſe, and wicked Crime, perſiſted ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49981:29"/>
long in a continued courſe of Weeping, till both his Eyes were out. And thus God in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſent upon each of them their wiſhes, and thereby manifeſted the innocency of the good Biſhop, and cleared him from Shame and Oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity.</p>
               <p>A Fellow hearing profane Curſing and Swearing condemned in the Pulpit by a learned Preacher, and that it never eſcaped Puniſhment, ſaid in a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, I have oft forſworn my ſelf, and yet my Right-hand is not a whit ſhorter than my Left; which words he had ſcarce uttered, when preſently ſuch an Inflammation aroſe in his Hand, that he was conſtrained to go to a Surgeon and get it cut off, leſt it ſhould infect his whole Body; and ſo his Right-hand became ſhorter than his Left, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of his Perjury which he ſo lightly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of.</p>
               <p>In the Town of <hi>Rutlinquen,</hi> a certain Paſſenger coming into an Inn, gave a Budget with a good ſum of Money therein, to his Hoſt to lay by: but when he demanded it again at his going away, the Hoſt deny'd it, and gave him bad Language, with many Mocks and Taunts; ſo the Traveller call'd him before a Judg, but having no Witneſſes, deſired to have him ſworn, which he without ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple offered to do, and wiſhed he might go to the Devil, if ever he received or concealed ſuch a Bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. But the Paſſenger as he was going out, meets two men, and being informed by him of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, offer him their Aſſiſtance, and returned back again to the Judg: theſe two unknown Perſons juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified that the Budget was delivered to the Hoſt, and that he had hid it in ſuch a place, at which the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49981:30"/>
Hoſt became aſtoniſhed, and by his countenance and geſture diſcovered his Guiltineſs; whereupon the Judg reſolved to ſend him to Priſon, but the two unknown Witneſſes (who were indeed Fiends of Hell) began to ſay, you ſhall not need, for we are ſent to puniſh his Wickedneſs; and having ſo ſaid, they hoiſted him up into the Air, where he vaniſhed with them, and was never after found.</p>
               <p>In the reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> there was in the City of <hi>London,</hi> one <hi>Ann Averyes</hi> a Widow, who forſwore her ſelf for a little Money that ſhe was to pay for ſix pound of Tow, at a Shop in <hi>Woodſtreet;</hi> and being ſuddenly ſurprized with the Juſtice of God for this Wickedneſs, ſhe immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell down ſpeechleſs, and caſt up at her Mouth in great abundance, and with an horrible ſtink, that matter which by Nature ſhould have bin voided downwards, and ſo died.</p>
               <p>There was a profane wretch in <hi>Germany,</hi> that almoſt at every word he ſpake, the Devil was at one end of it; if walking he chanced to tread awry and ſtumble, preſently the Devil was in his Mouth: and notwithſtanding the many Reproofs he had from his Neighbours, with ſerious advice to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and amend ſo deteſtable a Vice, yet all was in vain; for continuing this his preſumptuous Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and damnable cuſtom, as he was paſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Bridg, he fell down, and in his fall uttered theſe words, Hoiſt up with an hundred Devils; which he had no ſooner ſpoken, but the Devil whom he call'd for ſo oft, was at his Elbow to ſtrangle him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49981:30"/>
In the year 1551. at <hi>Megalapale</hi> near <hi>Voildſtat,</hi> at the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> the People being ſet on Drinking and Carouſing, a Woman in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, commonly named the Devil in her Oaths, till at length he being ſo often call'd on, came on a ſudden and carried her through the Gate aloft in the Air, before them all, who ran out aſtoniſhed, to ſee whither he would tranſport her; and ſeeing her hanging in the Air for a while without the Town, at length ſhe fell down dead to the Ground.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time there lived one that was both a monſtrous Swearer, and alſo otherwiſe very vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, who tho he was frequently admoniſhed to forſake his cuſtomary Swearing, and to amend his Life, yet it was all but loſt labour, for he would not at all liſten thereunto. And the Peſtilence being on a time in the City, he became infected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and thereupon he withdrew himſelf apart, with his Wife and a Kinſwoman into a Garden he had; and the Miniſters coming to admoniſh him, and exhort him to Repentance, he was ſo far from being touched in Conſcience, or any ways moved with their godly Admonitions, that he ſtrove ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to harden himſelf more and more in his Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs. And being one day ſwearing and denying God, and giving himſelf to the Devil, and calling for him with vehemency, the Devil came and ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him up preſently, and heaved him up into the Air, his Wife and Kinſwoman looking on, and ſeeing him fly over their Heads, he was never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſeen any more.</p>
               <p>A Popiſh Prieſt on a time thundring out bitter Curſes in the Pulpit againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> wiſhed if <hi>Luther</hi>'s Doctrine was true, that a Thunder-bolt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49981:31"/>
might ſtrike him to death; three days after a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tempeſt of Thunder and Lightning ariſing, the Prieſt ran to the Altar into the Church, and fell to his Prayers; but the Vengeance of God found him out and his Hypocriſy, ſo that he was ſtrucken in a manner dead with the Lightning; but coming to Life again, as they led him homewards through the Church-yard, another flaſh ſo ſcorch'd him, that he was burnt from the crown of his Head, to the ſole of the Foot, as black as a Shoo, ſo that he died with the manifeſt mark of God's Vengeance upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beza</hi> reports, that he knew a man in <hi>France</hi> of good parts, well inſtructed in Religion, and a Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Family, who in his anger Curſing, and bidding the Devil take one of his Children, had preſently his wiſh, for the Child was poſſeſſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately with a Spirit; from which tho by the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and continual Prayers of the Church, he was at length releaſed, yet before he came to his perfect Health he died.</p>
               <p>The like hapned to a Woman whom her Husband in anger devoted to the Devil with bitter Curſes; whereupon Satan aſſaulted her preſently, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived her of her Wits, ſo that ſhe could never be recovered.</p>
               <p>Another example, ſaith the ſame Author, hapned to a Perjurer that wittingly and wilfully forſwore himſelf, to the end to prejudice and deceive another: but he had no ſooner made an end of his falſe and wicked Oath, but a grievous Apoplex ſeized him, ſo that without ſpeaking any one word afterwards he died within a few days.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49981:31"/>
A decrepit Romiſh Prieſt being by the help of others heaved and lift up into the Pulpit, and choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Text out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. concerning the Lord's Supper, and taking occaſion to defend the Papiſtical errors of the Maſs, he uſed theſe or the like blaſphemous Speeches, O. <hi>Paul, Paul,</hi> if this Doctrine touching the receiving the Sacrament in both kinds be true, and if it be a wicked thing to receive it otherwiſe, then I wiſh the Devil would come to take me: and then (turning himſelf to the People) if the Pope's Doctrine concerning this point be not true, then I am the Devil's bond-ſlave; neither do I fear to pawn my Soul upon it. Theſe and many other blaſphemous words he uſed, till the Devil came indeed, in the likeneſs of a tall man, black and terrible, ſending before him ſuch a fearful noiſe and ſuch a wind, that the People fearing the Church falling on their Heads were greatly amazed; but he not able to hurt the reſt, took away the old lame Prieſt, being his devoted Bond-ſlave, and carried him ſo far, that he was never after heard of.</p>
               <p>In the year 1556. at St. <hi>Gallus</hi> in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> a certain man that earned his living by making clean rough foul Linen againſt the Sun, entring a Tavern, taſted ſo plentifully of the juice of the Grape, that he vomited out terrible Curſes againſt himſelf and others; amongſt the reſt he wiſhed if ever he went into the Fields to his old Occupation, that then the Devil might come and break his Neck; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his late words, and this his profane and wicked Execration, after ſleep had conquer'd his drink, and ſobriety reſtored his Senſes, he went again to his Trade; remembring his late words, but little regarding them: but however the Devil at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49981:32"/>
him at his appointed hour, in the likeneſs of a big ſwarthy man, and asked him if he remembred his promiſe, the Vow which he made the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and if it were not lawful for him to break his Neck; and ſo ſtruck the poor trembling man over the Shoulders, that his Feet and his Hands preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dried up, and there he lay not able to ſtir, till by help of men he was carried home, the Lord not giving the Devil ſo much power as he wiſhed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but yet permitting him to plague him on this ſort, for his Amendment, and our Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Schwartburgh,</hi> through a corrupt cuſtom, uſed commonly to wiſh that he might be drowned in a Privy; and as he wiſhed, ſo it hapned unto him, for he was ſo ſerved, and murdered at St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Monaſtery in <hi>Erford,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1148.</p>
               <p>The like befel a young Courtier at <hi>Mansfield,</hi> whoſe cuſtom was in any earneſt Aſſeveration to ſay, the Devil take me if it be not ſo; ſo the Devil took him indeed, whilſt he ſlept, and threw him out at a high Window; where tho by the goodneſs of God, he caught no great harm, yet he learnt by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to bridle his Tongue from all ſuch curſed Speeches, this being but a taſte of God's Wrath that is to fall upon ſuch wretches.</p>
               <p>A Woman giving her ſelf to the Devil, both Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul, did uſe moſt horrible Curſing and Oaths, both to her ſelf and others uſually at all times, and in a more effectual manner at a certain Wedding: and the People exhotting her to leave off her ſinful courſe of Life; yet ſhe not regarding their advice, continued in her profane wicked progreſs, till all the People were ſet at Dinner, and very
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49981:32"/>
merry, and then the Devil came in Perſon and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported her into the Air before them all, with moſt horrible outcries and roarings, and in that manner carried her round about the Town, ſo that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants were very terribly afraid; and then he tore her in four pieces, leaving in ſeveral Highways a quarter, that all that came by, might be witneſſes of the Puniſhment, and then returning to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, threw her Bowels on the Table before the Mayor of the Town, with theſe words, Behold theſe diſhes of Meat belong to thee, whom the like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction awaiteth, if thou doſt not amend thy wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Life.</p>
               <p>There is mention made in <hi>Luther</hi>'s Conferences, that divers Noble-men being ſtriving together at an Horſe-race, in their Courſe, cried <hi>The Devil take the laſt;</hi> and the laſt being a Horſe that broke looſe, the Devil hoiſted him up into the Air, and took him clean away.</p>
               <p>We read of a certain man that provided a ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Supper, and none of his invited Gueſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, he in a great Paſſion and Heat ſaid, If none of them will come, then let all the Devils in Hell come; and preſently came a number of thoſe helliſh Fiends, whom he not diſcerning from men, coming to welcom and entertain them, when he took them by the Hands, he perceiving Claws in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Fingers, he was moſt terribly amazed, and ran out of Doors with his Wife, and leſt none in the Houſe but a young Infant and a Fool ſitting by the Fire, whom the Devils had no power to hurt, neither any Body elſe, but devoured up the Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and ſo departed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49981:33"/>
One <hi>Hacket</hi> of <hi>Oundle</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> uſed in his earneſt talk, to curſe himſelf in this manner, If it be not true, then let a viſible confuſion come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, which afterwards happened to him; for fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into abominable Errors, he call'd himſelf Chriſt and Judg of the World, for which he was hanged in the <hi>33d</hi> year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> London.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>berg,</hi> before <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and divers Learned men, a Woman whoſe Daughter was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by a Spirit, confeſſed that by her curſe, that plague was faln upon her Child; for being angry at a time, ſhe bid the Devil take her; and no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſpoken the words, but the Devil did take her indeed, and poſſeſſed her in a moſt ſtrange man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>And a Woman of <hi>Neuburg</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> curſing her Son in her angry Paſſion, prayed to God ſhe might never ſee him again return alive, which came to paſs that very day; for he bathing himſelf in the Water was drown'd, and never returned to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alive, according to her ungodly wiſh.</p>
               <p>Alſo another Woman in <hi>Aſtorga,</hi> in her rage cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one of her Sons with deteſtable Maledictions, giving him to the Devils of Hell, and wiſhing they would fetch him out of her preſence, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther horrible Execrations: this being about ten of the Clock at Night, and the night being very dark, the Boy growing fearful hearing his Mother curſe ſo, went out into a little Court behind the Houſe, from which place he was preſently hoiſed up into the Air, by men in ſhew of grim Countenance, great Stature, and loathſom and horrible Geſture, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed cruel Fiends of Hell, and that with ſuch ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49981:33"/>
(as the Boy confeſſed) that it was not poſſible as he thought for any Bird to fly ſo faſt; and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down amongſt certain Mountains amongſt Buſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Briers, was trailed through the thickeſt of them, and ſo torn and rent not only in his Clothes, but alſo in his Hands and Face, and almoſt all his whole Body; at laſt the Boy remembring God, and beſeeching his merciful Favour and Aſſiſtance, the cruel Fiends brought him back again through the Air, and put him in at a little Window into a Chamber in his Father's Houſe, where after much ſearch and grief for him, he was found in this miſerable Condition, and almoſt diſtracted; and thus tho they had no power to deprive him of his Life, yet the Lord ſuffered them to afflict the Parents in the Son, for the good of both if they belonged to God.</p>
               <p>But above all, (ſays my Author) this is moſt ſtrange which happned in a Town of <hi>Meſina, Anno</hi> 1552. when a diolerick Father ſeeing his Son ſlack about his Buſineſs, wiſhed he might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtir from that place; which was no ſooner ſaid, but it was done, and his Son ſtuck faſt in the place, and could not by any means poſſible be removed, no not ſo much as to move or bend his Body, till by the prayers of the Faithful his pains were ſomewhat mitigated, tho not remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; three years he continued ſtanding with a Poſt at his back for his caſe, and four years ſitting, at the end whereof he died: nothing weakned all this while in his Underſtanding, but profeſſing the Faith, and not doubting of his Salvation in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. When any asked him at any time how he did? his uſual anſwer was, that he was faſtned of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49981:34"/>
God, and that it was not in mans Power, but God's Mercy to releaſe him.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> in his Acts and Monuments, makes mention of a certain young Gallant that was a monſtrous Swearer, who riding in the Company of divers Gentlemen, began to ſwear and moſt horribly blaſpheme the Name of God; and one in the Company telling him that he muſt one day an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for it, he in a great huff ſaid, Why takeſt thou thought for me? take thought for thy Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſheet. Well ſays the other, amend, for death gives no warning, and as ſoon comes a Lambs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin to the Market as an old Sheeps. Gods wounds (ſaid he) care not thou for me, raging ſtill on this manner worſe and worſe, till at length as they paſt on their Journey, they came riding over a great Bridg; upon which the Gentleman Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſpurred his Horſe, ſo that he leapt clear over the Battlement with the man on his Back, who as he was going, cry'd, Horſe and Man and all to the Devil.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1629. one <hi>Thomas Wilſon</hi> Labourer, a known and common Swearer and Blaſphemer of God's Name by Oaths and Curſes, and much given to drink to exceſs, upon a ſlight occaſion moved to diſpleaſure againſt his Wife, and not daring to do much violence to her, turned it upon himſelf, and with his Knife ſtabb'd himſelf and ſo died, many of his Friends and Neighbours being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Jervaſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Elwayes</hi> Lieutenant of the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> when he was hanged on <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acceſſary in the poiſoning of Sir <hi>Thomas Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> his Priſoner, confeſſed, that at his playing at
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49981:34"/>
Cards and Dice, he had often wiſhed that he might be hang'd if it were not ſo and ſo, and therefore (ſays he) this ſhameful death is juſtly come upon me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1603. A man that dwelt in <hi>Wimble Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> ſeeing two godly Perſons going in the Highway near to him, ſaid to one that was with him, I will dance, and ſwear, and ſwagger, to anger yonder Puritans; and ſo he did to their great Grief, but preſently the revenging hand of God fell upon him; ſo that immediately he was ſtrucken with Sickneſs, was carried home in a Cart, and three days after he died in a moſt fearful manner.</p>
               <p>About the beginning of <hi>April</hi> 1661. a Woman in <hi>Darbyſhire,</hi> having cozened a Boy of ſome Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, was charged with it, but ſhe ſtifly denyed it; and being further urged to confeſs the Truth, ſhe (in a fearful manner) prayed God that the Earth might open and ſwallow her up quick if ſhe had it, and immediately the Earth under her opened, and ſhe ſunk down into it; and being afterwards digged for, they found her nine Foot deep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Earth, and that very Money was found in her Pocket: this was atteſted by credible Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Peter,</hi> Son-in-law to <hi>Alexander</hi> Keeper of <hi>Newgate,</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, an horrible Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, upon every idle occaſion uſed to ſay, if it be not true, I pray God I may rot before I die, and accordingly God made him exemplary; for as he wiſhed, ſo it happened to him, for his Body rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away by piece-meal till he died.</p>
               <p>And a certain Maid having ſtoln and pilfred ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things out of her Miſtreſſes Houſe, and being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined about it, forſwore them, and wiſhed that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49981:35"/>
ſhe might rot, if ever ſhe touched them or knew of them; and being carried to Priſon about them, ſhe began there to rot and ſtink ſo, that they were forced to thruſt her out of Priſon into an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital, where ſhe in great Miſery repented of her foul Sin.</p>
               <p>Alſo one <hi>John Duncalf</hi> of <hi>Kings Swinford,</hi> in <hi>January</hi> 1677. coming to the Houſe of one <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fry Baby</hi> at <hi>Grangewell</hi> about three miles from <hi>Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verhampton,</hi> he begg'd of the Woman there Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and Drink; who formerly knowing him, and compaſſionating his Condition, freely gave him ſome; but while ſhe was ſtooping to draw him ſome drink, he ſtole her Bible, and ſold it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards<hi>:</hi> fort three Shillings to a Maid not far off, whereby the Woman came to hear-of it, and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her the Money, received it again, but could not hear what was become of the man. But a while after <hi>John Duncalf</hi> hearing it diſcourſed that he ſtole a Bible, grew very angry, and gave out threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning words againſt a young man that reported it; but being ſeverely charged with it, he did not only deny it with ſome fierceneſs, but execrated and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf, wiſhing his Hands might rot off if it were true; which words he had no ſooner uttered, but by his own Confeſſion to divers that came to ſee him in his miſerable Condition, he ſaid that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately thereupon he had an inward Horror and Trembling upon him, a dread and fear of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance of God, and the Juſtice of him from whom no ſecrets are hid; and that within a few days after his Curſing himſelf, his Fleſh began to look black at the wriſts of his Hands; and he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued divers Weeks with Faintneſs; and fearing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49981:35"/>
an Ague, was going for his Acquaintance; but not being able to go further, he laid himſelf down in a Barn, and there continued two days and nights before he was found, from whence he was removed to another Barn near <hi>Woolverhampton,</hi> and had a Keeper appointed him: his Fleſh began firſt to riſe in great knobs at his Wriſts and Knees, and to break and run with putrid Matter, the Fleſh ſhrunk from the Bones, his pain was exquiſite, the ſmell very offenſive, Worms bred in the putrid Fleſh, and his Hands and Legs fell off. And thus conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued he begging the Prayers of thoſe Divines that came to viſit him, and acknowledging the juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God for his Stealing, Lying, and Curſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſome Weeks a dreadful ſpectacle of the Divine Vengeance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1677. At <hi>Atherbury</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that kept a petty Alehouſe having much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted her ſelf to Oaths and Curſes, and one Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a neighbouring Woman coming thither for ſome ſtrong Drink ſhe had occaſion for, and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a piece of Money, ſhe would have two pence or three pence more for a former Debt, which the other reſolutely denied. The Hoſteſs began to ſwear, and uſe ſeveral profane and abominable wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and imprecations; as, God damn me, and the Devil burn me, if it be not ſo; which laſt words ſhe often repeated, thruſting the other Woman violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of her Houſe, ſhutting the Door, and lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it againſt her. Her Husband not long after coming home, wondered to find the Door faſt, but at laſt with one or two of his Neighbours, he forced it open, and to his great ſurprizal finds in the midſt of the Floor the Relicks of his Wife, one
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49981:36"/>
ſide of her Body and the Clothes on it, from the ſole of her Foot to the crown of her Head, burnt to aſhes, and nothing left but the Skeleton, or part of the Bones; whereas the other ſide remained whole, and the Clothes not ſo much as touch'd or ſing'd, tho it was obſerved that the Fleſh and Skin was all turned black.</p>
               <p>Much the like Story (as Reverend Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> tells us) was publiſhed not many years ago concerning a Maid in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A diſſolute young man (Servant to a Gentleman) who was much given to beaſtly Drunkenneſs, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſome of his Companions at <hi>Sangall</hi> in <hi>Switzerland</hi> to be merry, when they had drunk free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and extravagantly, he began to rail at and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with his Companions, and uſing many blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt God, he added this execration alſo; If I ſerve my Maſter any longer, I give my Body and Soul to the Devil; and ſtaying there all night, in the morning he began to think of what he had ſaid the night before, yet having no other means of ſubſiſtence, he reſolved to return to his Maſter's Service; but at his return when he was not far from his Maſters Houſe, a man met him clad in black and fearful to behold, who ſaid to him, Come fellow, I am now ready to take that which is my right, and which thou gaveſt me yeſterday; and ſo taking him by the Hand (to his great Horrour and Amazement) the Devil threw him to the ground, and ſo vaniſhed: and not long after this miſerable young man being found by ſome of his Neighbours, his Hands and Feet were drawn together; and being brought to a Lodging, he had the uſe of all his Limbs taken from him, and ſo continued till he died miſerably.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:49981:36"/>
A Serving-man in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> for every trifle uſed to ſwear by God's blood, and would not be warned by his Friends, till at length falling into a grievous Sickneſs, he was again much perſwaded by his Friends to repent, which counſel he ſtill reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hearing the Bell toll, in the very pains of Death, he ſtarted up, God's wounds the Bell tolls for me, but he ſhall not have me yet; whereupon the Blood iſſued out in a moſt fearful manner from all the joints of his Body, from Mouth, Noſe, Wriſts, Knees, Heels, and Toes, and other parts of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and ſo he died, as Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> relates.</p>
               <p>Another example of like Puniſhment befel one Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> a great Swearer, who going forth a Hunting or Hawking on the Lord's-day or a Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, and not finding game and ſpeeding to his mind, he went to an Ale-houſe at <hi>Puckeridg</hi> five miles from <hi>Ware,</hi> in the way to <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and call'd for drink, beginning to ſwear after his unhappy Cuſtom, ſaying, By God's blood this is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky day: and preſently after he bled at the Noſe, which ſo vexed him that he began to rail and blaſpheme the Name of God, ſwearing Paſſion, Wounds, Nails, Fleſh, Blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till at laſt he proceeded further to bleed at the Ears, Eyes, Wriſts, joints of his Hands, and of all his Body, at the Navil and Fundament, in a wonderful great quantity, and ſtreams of Blood, blaring out his Tongue in a fearful manner as black as Pitch, ſo that no Perſon durſt come near him: this continued till the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Death made an end of him; next day (ſays the Publiſher hereof) the Body was laid in a Cart, carried to <hi>Standon,</hi> and buried in the Highway.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49981:37"/>
                  <hi>Michael</hi> a Jewiſh Rabbin, as he was ſwearing and blaſpheming the Name of Jeſus, fell down and broke his Neck.</p>
               <p>Three Soldiers paſſing through a Wood in the Country of <hi>Samurta,</hi> there aroſe a tempeſt of Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning, and one of them to ſhew his contempt of God and his Judgments, burſt forth into ſwearing and blaſphemy; but the Tempeſt tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a Tree, it fell upon him, and cruſht him to pieces.</p>
               <p>One who for twelve or ſixteen years together uſed to ſwear by God's Arms, in the end his own Arm being hurt with a Knife, could not be healed by any means, but rankled and feſtered from day to day, at length ſo rotted, that it fell away piece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal, and he himſelf through the anguiſh and pain thereof died.</p>
               <p>I my ſelf (faith a godly Divine that wrote late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) knew two moſt notorious Swearers that brake their Necks, the one with a fall down a pair of Stairs, and the other from his Horſe.</p>
               <p>At a Village called <hi>Benevides</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> two young men being together in the Fields, there ſuddenly aroſe a terrible Tempeſt, and withal ſo violent a Whirlwind, that it amazed the beholders: the two young men ſeeing the fury of it coming towards them, run as faſt as poſſible they might, but yet it overtook them; and they fearing to be hoiſted up into the Air by it, fell down flat upon the Earth, where the Whirlwind whisked round about them for a pretty while, and then paſſed forwards, and the one of them roſe in ſuch an Agony, that he was ſcarce able to ſtand, and the other lying ſtill and not ſtirring, ſome other that ſtood under a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49981:37"/>
Hedg a far off, went to ſee how he did, and found him ſtark dead, with his Bones ſo cruſh'd that the joints of his Arms and Legs turned every way, as tho his Body had bin made of Moſs; his Tongue alſo was pull'd out of his Mouth by the Roots, and could never be found, which was the more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe he was noted to be an outragious ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and blaſphemer of God's Name.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Tubing</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> (as the Hiſtory tells us) a Boy uſed to invent ſuch new Oaths as were not common; but the Lord ſent a Canker or ſome worſe Diſeaſe that did eat out his Tongue, the inſtrument wherewith he blaſphemed God.</p>
               <p>A certain man (ſays Mr. <hi>Bolton)</hi> who in his Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time was given exceedingly to the fearful ſin of Swearing, had his Heart on his death-bed ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly filled with enraged greedineſs after it, that he deſperately deſired the ſtanders by to help him with Oaths, and to ſwear for him, tho himſelf in the mean time ſwore as faſt and furiouſly as he could.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1649. about the end of <hi>June,</hi> there was a Soldier at <hi>Ware,</hi> going with ſome others to waſh themſelves in the River; and this Soldier finding the Water ſhallow, he asked if there were no deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er a place for him to ſwim in, and ſome told him that there was not far off a deep pit, but that it was very dangerous, and therefore adviſed him to take heed how he went into it: to whom he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, God damn me, if it be as deep as Hell I will go into it, which accordingly he did, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſunk to the Bottom, never riſing again, but was there drowned.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49981:38"/>
                  <hi>November</hi> 1626. a Serving-man being at a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> threatned to ſwear the Conſtable out of the Town if he came there; but in a drunken fit as he was running after one to make him pledg him a pint of Sack at a draught, he fell down the Stairs and died immediately.</p>
               <p>A Fiſher-man whom I knew (ſays Mr. <hi>Beadle</hi> in his Diary) bringing Mackarel to a Port-town in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> where the People (becauſe they were the firſt that came that year) preſſing eagerly to buy them, ſome againſt his Will being entred into the Boat, he took up a Stone and ſwore by the Name of God he would make them ſtand farther off, whereupon he ſunk down inſtantly, and ſoon after died.</p>
               <p>I of my own certain knowledg knew a Man in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> a cuſtomary profane deſperate Swearer, who going out on a time, with ſome Neighbours on foot a Hunting, it happened that he eſpied an Hare upon her Seat in his Range, ſo he ſwore a great Oath or two, ſhe's here, and putting up the Hare he ran over two or three Lands and fell down, the reſt of the Company following their Game be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got three or four Cloſes from him; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt the Hare, and not ſeeing this man coming, they went back to ſee what was the cauſe of his not coming, and finding him in the ſame place where he fell, they turned him up, and he was ſtark dead.</p>
               <p>There is no ſurer ſign of a wicked Perſon than common and cuſtomary Swearing, ſuch ſhould be ſerved as <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ſerved a Citizen of <hi>Paris,</hi> that ſeared his Lips for ſwearing with an hot Iron; and when ſome ſaid that it was too
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49981:38"/>
great Cruelty, he anſwered, I would to God that with fearing mine own Lips with an hot Iron, I could baniſh out of my Realm all abuſe of Oaths.</p>
               <p>Raſhneſs is a fault in any human Action, but in no Caſes more dangerous than in the imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Divine Judgments: men had need to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate and be well adviſed before they appeal to Heaven for Vengeance; for ofttimes the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of theſe raſh People are heard by God, and anſwered beyond their expectation, to their great Terror and Amazement, as plainly appears by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the before mentioned Examples.</p>
               <p>And infinite more Examples might be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, demonſtrating the diſpleaſure of Almighty God againſt the provoking ſin of profane Swearing and Curſing, and the ſeverity of his Juſtice in the ſignal puniſhments inflicted by him upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous cuſtomary practiſers thereof. But I hope the peruſal and ſerious Conſideration of theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſet down, may be ſufficient motives not only to bring all rational Perſons guilty of ſuch wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to a ſight of their profaneneſs, but alſo to a ſenſe of the great danger they are in, and be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by moved and incited to a firm purpoſe, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt reſolution of Amendment, and a total forſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this their accuſtomed abominable Sin.</p>
               <p>But if neither Law, Scripture, nor Example will prevail with them, then may that of the holy Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt be fitly applied to them; <hi>Ye imagine miſchief in your heart upon the Earth, and your hands deal with wickedneſs. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly are froward even from their Mothers Womb. They are as venom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> as the poiſon of a Serpents, even like the deaf Adder that ſtoppeth her Ears<hi>:</hi> Which refuſeth to hear the voice</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:49981:39"/>
                  <hi>of the Charmer, charm he never ſo wiſely.</hi> Pſal. 58. 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p>However let ſuch profligate preſumptuous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, provoking Sinners aſſuredly know, <hi>That the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his Name in vain.</hi> Exod. 20. 7. <hi>He that dwelleth in Heaven ſhall laugh them to ſcorn, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion. Then ſhall he ſpeak unto them in his Wrath, and vex them in his ſore Diſpleaſure.</hi> Pſal. 2. 4, 5. For tho God ſometimes have leaden Feet, yet the wicked find that he hath iron Hands; <hi>For God ſhall wound the head of his Enemies, and the hairy Scalp of ſuch an one as goeth on ſtill in his Wickedneſs.</hi> Pſal. 68. 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>An Abſtract of the Laws made againſt the profanation of the Lord's-day, commonly called Sunday.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Conceive it will not be altogether improper (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I proceed to give an account of the Laws made for the obſervation of the Lords day) to ſet down an Abſtract here of the Statute of <hi>E.</hi> 6. about the Sacrament, and of that of Q. <hi>M.</hi> about diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbing Miniſters; likewiſe the Statute <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. about profane ſpeaking or jeſting with the Name of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then to proceed to the other Laws.</p>
               <p>By the Statute 1 <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. it is Enacted,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That none ſhall ſpeak or do any thing in contempt of the moſt Holy Sacrament, in pain of Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49981:39"/>
and to make Fine and Ranſom at the King's Will.</p>
                  <p>Three Juſtices of the Peace <hi>(Quor. unus)</hi> have power to take Information by the Oaths of two lawful Perſons (at leaſt) concerning the Offence aforeſaid, and to bind over by Recognizances every Accuſer and Witneſs in five Pound apiece to appear at the next Seſſions to give Evidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Offendors, who are there to be enquired of before three Juſtices or more, by the Oaths of twelve men, and alſo indicted if the matter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged againſt them be found true; the Offence to be proſecuted within three Months.</p>
               </q>
               <p>By the Statute 1 <hi>M. Seſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3. it is Enacted,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That if any ſhall diſturb a Preacher lawfully Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in his open Sermon or Collation, he ſhall be by the Conſtables or Church-wardens of the Pariſh, brought before a Juſtice of the Peace, who upon due Accuſation ſhall commit him to ſafe Cuſtody, and within ſix days after, together with another Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, ſhall diligently examine the Fact; who if they find cauſe, ſhall commit him to the common Goal, there to remain for three Months, and from thence to the next Quarter-Seſſions; at Which upon the parties Reconciliation, and entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Bond for good Behaviour for one whole Year (at diſcretion of the Juſtices in Seſſions) he ſhall be releaſed; but if he perſiſt ſtill in his Obſtinacy, he ſhall remain in Priſon without Bail, until he ſhall reconcile, and be penitent for his Offence.</p>
                  <p>He that reſcues an Offendor in this kind, ſhall ſuffer like Impriſonment as aforeſaid, and beſides ſhall forfeit five Pounds to the King.</p>
                  <p>The Inhabitants of a Town that ſuffer ſuch an
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49981:40"/>
Offendor to eſcape, ſhall forfeit five Pounds, being preſented before the Juſtices of Peace in Seſſions within the County or Corporation where the eſcape was made.</p>
                  <p>Juſtices of Peace, Aſſize, and Oyer and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner, and Mayors, and head Officers of Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, have power to hear and determin theſe Offences, and to impoſe the Fines aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>This Act ſhall not reſtrain the juriſdiction of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, howbeit none ſhall be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here for one Offence.</p>
               </q>
               <p>By the Statute 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 21. <q>None ſhall in any Stage-play, Shew, May game or Pageant, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely uſe the Name of God, Chriſt Jeſus, the Holy Ghoſt, or Trinity, on pain of ten Pounds, to be divided between the King and Proſecutor.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It's ſaid that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great made Laws for the ſtrict obſervation of the Lord's Day, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that through all the Roman Empire all ſervile Employments ſhould ceaſe on thoſe days: he preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo a form for the Legions of Soldiers to be uſed both on the Sabbath-days and other days; and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf uſed to ſhew much Reverence and Attention to the Word of God, ſo that many times he would ſtand up all the Sermon time: and when ſome of his Courtiers told him that it would tend to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement, he anſwered that it was in the Service of the great God, who was no reſpecter of Perſons.</p>
               <p>By the Statute 1 <hi>Eliz. Ch.</hi> 2. <q>Every Perſon is to reſort to their Pariſh Church, or (upon let thereof) to ſome other, every Sunday and Holy-day, upon pain to be puniſhed by Cenſures of the Church, and alſo to forfeit twelve pence for every Default, to be levied by the Church-wardens there for the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49981:40"/>
uſe of the Poor, upon the Offendor's Goods by way of Diſtreſs, and for want of Diſtreſs, to be committed to ſome Priſon until the ſame be paid.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And by the Statute 23 <hi>El. Ch.</hi> 1. <q>Every Perſon not repairing to Church, (according to the Statute aforeſaid) ſhall forfeit twenty Pounds for every Month they ſo make Default; and if the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor is not able to pay, and do not pay within three Months after Judgment, then to be committed to Priſon, and there to remain until he have ſatisfied the ſame, or ſhall conform himſelf and go to the Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By the Statute 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 4.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>The King may refuſe the twenty Pounds a Month for abſenting from the Church, and take in lieu thereof two third parts of the abſenters Lands and Leaſes; but here he ſhall not include the Recuſants Manſion-houſe, nor demiſe the two third parts to a Recuſant, or to any other for a Recuſants uſe.</p>
                  <p>The Church-wardens and Conſtables of every Pariſh, or one of them, or (if there be none ſuch) then the High-Conſtable of the Hundred there ſhall preſent once every year at the general Seſſions of the Peace, the monthly abſence from Church of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Popiſh Recuſant, and then Children being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Age of nine years, and their Servants, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Age of their Children, as near as they can know them, on pain to forfeit reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for every ſuch default twenty Shillings; which Preſentment the Clerk of the Peace, or Town-Clerk ſhall record without Fee, on pain of forty Shillings.</p>
                  <p>If upon ſuch Preſentment (being the firſt) the Recuſant be convicted, the Officer that preſents
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49981:41"/>
him ſhall have forty Shillings reward, to be levied by Warrant upon the Recuſants Goods and Eſtate, as the more part of the Juſtices of Peace ſhall think fit.</p>
               </q>
               <p>But Note, that his Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects, Diſſenting from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified according to the late Statute of Indulgence, are exempted from the Penalties of theſe Statutes.</p>
               <p>The command of the Sabbath hath a ſpecial me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento prefixed to it, which may not only note to us, that we are by this Memento, <hi>Remember thou keep Holy the Sabbath-day,</hi> to obſerve the Lord's zeal for the obſervance thereof, but we are thereby put in mind, timely to lay aſide our worldly Buſineſs, and get our Hearts into readineſs for the entertainment of God into the ſame. And altho nothing is more acceptable to God than the true and ſincere Worſhip and Service of him according to his Holy Will, and that the Holy keeping of the Lord's-day is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the true Worſhip and Service of God: Yet the People of this Kingdom having enjoyed a long continued ſeries of Peace, Plenty, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, inſtead of rendring thanks to Almighty God for this great Bleſſing, and of ſerving him in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs of Life and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they on the contrary, like the idolatrous Jews upon the making of their Golden-Calf, <hi>they ſat down to eat and drink, and roſe up to play,</hi> Exod. 32. 6. 1 Cor. 10. 7. Nay the people of this Realm were ſo entirely devoted to Games and Paſtimes, that they could not, or would not forbear them upon the Lord's Day, but ſpent that day in the ſervice of Satan, which Almighty God hath hallowed and commanded to be ſet apart for the Service and Worſhip of himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49981:41"/>
For this Day in many Places of the Realm being prophaned and neglected by a diſorderly ſort of People, in exerciſing and frequenting Bear-bait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Bull-baiting, Enterludes, Common Plays, and other unlawful Exerciſes and Paſtimes thereon. And for that many Quarrels, Bloodſheds and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Inconveniencies did grow by the Reſort and Concourſe of People going out of their own Pariſhes, to ſuch diſorderly and unlawful Exerciſes, and Paſtimes, neglecting Divine Service both in their own Pariſhes and elſewhere.</p>
               <p>Therefore by the Statute 1 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. it is enacted, <q>That there ſhall be no Meetings, Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, or Concourſe of People out of their own Pariſhes on the Lord's Day, within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> or any the Dominions thereof, for any Sports or Paſtimes whatſoever, nor any Bear-baiting, Bull-baiting, Enterludes, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Plays, or other unlawful Exerciſes or Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times uſed by any Perſon or Perſons within their own Pariſhes, and that every Perſon and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons offending in any the Premiſſes, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for every Offence three Shillings and four Pence, to the uſe of the Poor of the Pariſh where the Offence ſhall be committed. And if any one Juſtice of the Peace of the County, or the Chief Officer or Officers of any City, Borough or Town-corporate, where ſuch Offence ſhall be committed, upon his or their view, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Party, or Proof of any one or more Witneſs by Oath, which ſuch Magiſtrate hath power to adminiſter, ſhall find any Perſon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending in the Premiſſes, the ſaid Magiſtrate ſhall give Warrant under his or their Hand and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49981:42"/>
Seals to the Conſtable or Church-wardens of the Pariſh or Pariſhes where ſuch Offence ſhall be committed, to levy the ſaid Penalties ſo to be aſſeſſed by way of Diſtreſs and Sale of the Goods of every ſuch Offender, rendring the ſaid Offenders the overplus; and in Default of ſuch Diſtreſs, that the Party offending be ſet publickly in the Stocks by the ſpace of three Hours. And if any Man be ſued or impeached for the Execution of this Law, he may plead the general Iſſue, and give the matter of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in evidence; and no Man to be impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this Act, except he be called in queſtion within one Month next after the Offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. The Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction not to beabridged by this Act, but that the Eccleſiaſtical Court may puniſh the ſame Offence, as if this Act had not been made.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Statute 1 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. only prohibiting unlawful Sports, Games and Paſtimes, on the Lord's Day; Carriers, Waggoners, Wayr-men, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Drovers, being out of the Statute, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Veneration for the Lord's Day, kindneſs for themſelves, nor pity for their Beaſts, did make a Common practiſe of Travelling upon this Day; and Butchers did uſually kill and fell Victuals on the Lord's Day. So in the 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. An Act was made, prohibiting Carriers, Drovers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to travel on this Day, on pain of twenty Shillings every Offence; and Butchers for killing and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Victuals thereon, on pain of ſix Shillings and eight Pence for every Offence. But this Statute ſtanding but upon contiunance, and expiring after the end of the firſt Seſſion of Parliament then next
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49981:42"/>
following: Several of theſe Perſons returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (like the Dog to his Vomit) to their former accuſtomed Prophaneſs.</p>
               <p>And tho this Statute 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2. was by the Statute 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 4. continued and made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual, yet the unnatural uncivil Civil War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and Parliament breaking out ſhortly after, this Statute was much neglected and ſeldom put in Execution; two Witneſſes being required for the conviction of the Offender, which was troubleſome.</p>
               <p>So by the Statute 29 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 7. it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That all Perſons whatſoever ſhall on the Lord's Day apply themſelves to the obſervation of the ſame, by exerciſing themſelves thereon in the Duties of Piety and true Religion, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and privately. And no Tradeſman, Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, Workman, Labourer, or other Perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſhall do or exerciſe any worldly Labours, Buſineſs or Work of their ordinary Callings, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord's Day: (Works of Neceſſity and Charity only excepted) And every Perſon being of the Age of Fourteen Years or upwards of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending in the Premiſſes, ſhall for every ſuch Offence forfeit the Sum of five Shillings; and no Perſon or Perſons whatſoever ſhall publickly cry, ſhew forth or expoſe to Sale, any Wares, Merchandizes, Fruit, Herbs, Goods or Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels whatſoever upon the Lord's Day, or any part thereof, upon pain of forfeiting the ſame Goods ſo cryed, or ſhewed forth, or expoſed to Sale.</p>
                  <p>And no Drover, Horſe-courſer, Waggoner, Butcher or Higler, their or any of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49981:43"/>
ſhall travel, or come into his or their Inn, or Lodging upon the Lord's Day, or any part thereof, upon pain of twenty Shillings for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch Offence; and none ſhall uſe, imploy, or travel upon the Lord's Day, with any Boat, Wherry, Lighter or Barge, except it be upon extraordinary occaſion, to be allowed by a Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace of the County, or Head Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, or Juſtice of the Peace of the City, Borough, or Town-Corporate, where the Fact ſhall be committed, on pain of five Shillings for every ſuch Offence; and if any Perſon ſo offending in any of the Premiſſes ſhall be thereof convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before any Juſtice of the Peace of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or chief Officer or Juſtice of the Peace of the City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where the Offence ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, upon his or their view, or confeſſion of the Party, or proof of any one or more Witneſſes (which Oath the ſaid Magiſtrates are impower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to adminiſter) then the ſaid Juſtice, or chief Officer or Officers, ſhall give Warrant under his or their Hand, to the Conſtable or Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the Pariſh or Pariſhes where the Offence ſhall be committed, to ſeize the ſaid Goods ſo ſhewed forth, or put to ſale, as aforeſaid, and to fell the ſame: And to levy the ſaid other For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures or Penalties by way of Diſtreſs and Sale of the Goods of every ſuch Offender diſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, rendring them the overplus of the Money raiſed thereby; and in Default of ſuch Diſtreſs, or in caſe of Inſufficiency or Inability to pay, the Party offending to be ſet publickly in the Stocks by the ſpace of two Hours. And all Forfeitures to be imployed to the uſe of the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49981:43"/>
Poor of the Pariſh where the ſaid Offence ſhall be committed: Save that any ſuch Juſtice, May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may out of the ſaid Forfeitures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the informer according to their Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo as ſuch Reward exceed not a third part of the Forefeitures.</p>
                  <p>But this Act is not to extend to the prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of dreſſing of Meat in Families, or dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or ſelling of Meat in Inns, Cooks-ſhops or Victualling-houſes, for ſuch as otherwiſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be provided, nor to the crying or ſelling of Milk before nine of the Clock in the Morning, and after-four in the Afternoon.</p>
                  <p>No Perſon to be impeached, proſecuted, or moleſted for any Offence before mentioned, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be within ten Days after the Offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
                  <p>And if any Perſon ſhall travel upon the Lord's Day, and be robbed, the Inhabitants of the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſhall not anſwer for the Robbery, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on notice of ſuch Robbery to them or ſome of them given, or Hue and Cry for the ſame to be made, they ſhall make or cauſe to be made freſh purſuit after the ſaid Offenders with Horſemen and Footmen, according to the Statute 27 <hi>Eliz.</hi> upon pain to forfeit as much Money to the King's Majeſty as might have been recovered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them by the Party robbed.</p>
                  <p>And no Perſon or Perſons whatſoever upon the Lord's Day ſhall ſerve or execute any Writ, Proceſs, Warrant, Order, Judgment or Decree (except in Caſes of Treaſon, Felony or Breach of the Peace) but that the Service thereof ſhall be utterly void, and the Perſon or Perſons ſo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49981:44"/>
ſerving or executing the ſame, ſhall be as lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Suit of the Party grieved, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Damages to him for doing thereof, as if he or they had done the ſame without any Writ, Proceſs, Warrant, Order, Judgment or Decree at all.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Having ſhewed what Proviſion the Law makes for the Obſervation of the Lord's Day. I ſhall proceed in the next Chapter to give an Account what ſome Texts of Holy Writ command in ſuch Caſe to be obſerved.</p>
               <p>Note that by the Statute 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22. No Shoe-maker ſhall put his Wares to ſale upon Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days, on pain of three Shillings and four Pence, and alſo to forfeit the full value of the Wares ſold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the ſeveral Texts or Places of Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the due Obſervation and Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <q>REmember the Sabbath Day, to keep it holy: Six Days ſhalt thou labour, and do all thy work; but the Seventh Day is the Sabbath of thy Lord thy God: in it thou ſhalt not do any work, Thou, nor thy Son, nor thy Daughter, thy Man Servant, nor thy Maid Servant, nor thy Cattel, nor thy Stranger that is within thy Gates. For in Six Days the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that in them is, and reſted the ſeventh day; wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeventh day, and hallowed it, <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 8, 9, 10, 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:49981:44"/>
                  <q>Six days thou ſhalt do thy work, and on the ſeventh day thou ſhalt reſt: that thine Ox and thine Aſs may reſt, and the Son of thy Handmaid, and the Stranger may be refreſhed, <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 12.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Speak thou alſo unto the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, Verily my Sabbaths ye ſhall keep; for it is a ſign between me and you, throughout your Generations, that ye may know that I am the Lord, that doth ſanctify you: Ye ſhall keep the Sabbath therefore; for it is holy unto you. Every one that defileth it, ſhall ſurely be put to death: for whoſoever doth any work therein, that Soul ſhall be cut off from amongſt the People. Six days may work be done, but in the ſeventh is the Sabbath of reſt, holy to the Lord: whoſoever doth any work in the Sabbath day, he ſhall ſurely be put to death, <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 13, 14, 15.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Six days thou ſhalt work, but on the ſeventh day thou ſhalt reſt, in Earing-time, and in Harveſt thou ſhalt reſt, <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Ye ſhall keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary, I am the Lord, <bibl>
                        <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 30. 26. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And while the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs they found a Man that gathered Sticks upon the Sabbath-day, and they that found him gathering Sticks, brought him unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and unto all the Congregation. And they put him in Ward, becauſe it was not declared what ſhould be done to him. And the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Man ſhall ſurely be put to death: all the Congregation ſhall ſtone him with Stones; and all the Congregation brought him without the Gamp, and ſtoned him with Stones, and he died; as the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes.</hi> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 15. 32, 33, 34, 35, 36.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Keep the Sabbath-day to ſanctify it, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee; ſix days thou ſhalt labour
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49981:45"/>
and do all thy Work; but the ſeventh Day is the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of the Lord thy God; in it thou ſhalt not do any Work, thou, nor thy Son, nor thy Daughter, nor thy Man ſervant, nor thy Maid-ſervant, nor thine Ox, nor thine Aſs, nor any of thy Cattel, nor thy Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that is within thy Gates; that thy Man-ſervant, and thy Maid-ſervant may reſt as well as thou. <bibl>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 12, 13, 14.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Six days ſhall Work be done, but on the ſeventh day there ſhall be to you an Holy day, a Sabbath of Reſt to the Lord; whoſoever doth work therein ſhall be put to death. <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 35. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Bleſſed is the Man that doth this, and the Son of Man that layeth hold on it: that keepeth the Sabbath from polluting it, and keepeth his hand from doing any Evil. <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>If thou turn away thy Foot from the Sabbath, from doing thy Pleaſure on my Holy day, and call the Sabbath a Delight, the Holy of the Lord, Honourable, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own pleaſures, nor ſpeaking thine own words. Then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to ride upon the high places of the Earth, and feed thee with the Heritage of <hi>Jacob</hi> thy Father: for the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it. <bibl>
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 13, 14.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And on the ſeventh day, ye ſhall have an holy Convocation, ye ſhall do no ſervile Work, <bibl>
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 38. 25.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thus ſaith the Lord, Take heed to your ſelves, and hear no Burden on the Sabbath day, nor bring it in by the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Neither carry forth a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den out of your Houſes on the Sabbath-day, neither do ye any work, but hallow the Sabbath-day; as I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded your Fathers. But if you will not hearken to me to hallow the Sabbath-day, and not to bear a Burden,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49981:45"/>
even entring in at the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-day: Then will I kindle a Fire in the Gates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and it ſhall devour the Palaces of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and it ſhall not be quenched. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 21, 22, and 27.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou haſt deſpiſed mine Holy things, and haſt profan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Sabbaths. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 8.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Moreover, this they have done unto me, they have defiled my Sanctuary in the ſame day, and have profaned my Sabbaths. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23. 38.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> How long refuſe ye to keep my Commandments and my Laws? See for that the Lord hath given you the Sabbath, therefore he giveth you on the ſixth day the Bread of two days; abide ye every Man in his place, let no Man go out of his place on the ſeventh day. So the People reſted on the ſeventh day. <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 28, 29, 30.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Moreover alſo I gave them my Sabbaths to be a ſign between me and them, that they might know that I am the Lord that ſanctify them. But the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> rebelled againſt me in the Wilderneſs: they walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not in my Statutes, and they deſpiſed my Judgments, which if a Man keep he ſhall even live in them. And my Sabbaths they greatly polluted: then I ſaid I would pour out my Fury upon them in the Wilderneſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 12, 13.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In thoſe days I ſaw in <hi>Judah</hi> ſome treading Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes on the Sabbath, and bringing in Sheaves, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Aſſes; alſo Wine, Grapes, and Figs, and all manner of Burdens which they brought into <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on the Sabbath-day, and I teſtified againſt them in the day wherein they ſold Victuals. There dwelt Men of <hi>Tyre</hi> alſo therein, which brought Fiſh, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Wares; and ſold on the Sabbath unto the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Judah,</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Then I contended
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49981:46"/>
with the Nobles of <hi>Judah,</hi> and ſaid unto them, what Evil thing is that ye do and profane the Sabbath day? Did not your Fathers thus, and did not God bring all this Evil upon us, and upon this City? Yet ye bring more Wrath upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by profaning the Sabbath. <bibl>
                        <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13. 15, 16, 17, 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Several other Places of Scripture might be here inſerted to this purpoſe; but it being plain and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious that many Perſons are ſo emboldned by their cuſtomary and continued Practice in the Prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord's Day, that (to the great grief of every good Chriſtian) they contemn the Law, neglect God's Houſe, and deſpiſe his Holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, ridicule all good Counſel and Advice, and ſtop their Ears to all Godly Perſwaſions.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore (for the Terror of ſuch obſtinate Sinners) in this next Chapter, ſet down ſeveral Examples of God's Indignation and Wrath poured down upon the Heads of cuſtomary and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Profaners of the Lord's Day; in hopes that thereby they may be brought to take notice of that Saying of the Poet,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Fœlix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>An happy Man is he, that can beware</l>
                  <l>Of others harms, and of himſelf take care.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And ſo intitle themſelves to that promiſe of God: <hi>When the wicked man turneth away from his Wickedneſs that he hath committed, and doth that which is lawful and right, he ſhall ſave his Soul alive.</hi> Ezek. 18. 27.</p>
               <p>And by turning to the Lord, and forſaking their wicked Courſes, prevent the like Judgments from
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49981:46"/>
falling upon their own Heads. <hi>For to the Lord our God belong Mercies, and Forgiveneſſes, tho we have rebelled againſt him: Neither have we obeyed the Voice of the Lord our God, to walk in his Laws which be ſet before us.</hi> Dan. 9. 9, 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>An Account of ſeveral Inſtances of God's ſevere Juſtice, and Puniſhments that have befaln preſumptuous, cuſtomary Profaners of the Lord's Day, commonly called <hi>Sunday.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT has been obſerved, and ſtill taken notice of, that moſt of thoſe Criminals that make their Ignominious <hi>Exit</hi> at the Gallows, who come to a ſight and ſence of their Sins, and make Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Wickedneſs, and beg pardon at God's Hands for their ſinful courſe of Life; do bewail their neglect of the due Obſervation of the Lord's Day, and warn others by their Example, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſuch Wickedneſs, and of the ſad Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that attend thoſe that make a practice of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning the Lord's Day.</p>
               <p>This is the Market-day of the Soul, wherein the Lord in a more ſpecial manner uſeth to meet his People, to diſpenſe his Bleſſings and Graces in and by his holy Ordinances, to thoſe that humbly and reverently attend upon him therein: The care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sanctification of it, keeps up the Power of Godlineſs in our Hearts and Lives, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners thereof have often been puniſhed with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49981:47"/>
ſignal Judgments of God's ſevere Juſtice, as may partly appear by the following Examples.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Bedfordſhire,</hi> a Match at Foot-ball being made and appointed on the Sabbath-day in the Afternoon, whilſt two were in the Belfry toling of the Bell to call the Company together, there was ſuddenly heard a Clap of Thunder, and a Flaſh of Lightning was ſeen by ſome that ſate in the Church-Porch, coming through a dark Lane, and flaſhing in their Faces, which much terrified them, and paſſing through the Porch into the Belfry, it tripp'd up his Heels that was toling the Bell, and ſtruck him ſtark dead; and the other that was with him, was ſo ſorely blaſted therewith, that ſhortly after he died alſo.</p>
               <p>At a place called <hi>Tidworth,</hi> on the Sabbath-day many being met together to play at Foot-ball in the Church-yard, one of them had his Leg broken, which preſently gangreenizing, he forthwith died thereof.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Aleceſter</hi> in <hi>Warwickſhire,</hi> a luſty young Women went to a Green not far off, where ſhe ſaid ſhe would dance as long as ſhe could ſtand, but while ſhe was dancing (it being upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day) God ſtruck her with a violent Diſeaſe, whereof within two days after ſhe died.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the ſame Place not long after, a young Man preſently after the Evening Service was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, brought a pair of Cudgels into the Street, near to the Miniſter's Houſe, calling upon divers to play with him, but they all refuſing, at length came one who took them up; ſaying, tho I never play'd in my Life, yet I will play one Bout now; but ſhortly after he was jeſting with a young
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49981:47"/>
Maid, he took up a Birding Piece, which was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſaying, <hi>Have at thee;</hi> and the Piece going off, ſhot her in the Face, whereof ſhe immediatly died, for which Act, he forfeited all his Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and underwent the Law.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Wooton</hi> in the ſame County, a Miller going forth on the Sabbath-day to a Wake, when he came Home at Night, found his Houſe, Mill, and all he had burnt down to the Ground.</p>
               <p>And at <hi>Woolſton</hi> in the ſame County, many looſe Perſons kept a Whitſon-Ale, and had a Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice-dancing on the Sabbath-day, in a Smith's Barn, to the great Grief of the Godly Miniſter there, who uſed his utmoſt endeavour to reſtrain them from ſuch Profaneneſs, but in vain; ſo as it pleaſed God ſhortly after a Fire kindled in that Smith's Shop, which burnt it down, with his Houſe and Barn; and raging furiouſly, going ſome-times with the Wind, and ſometimes againſt it, it burnt down many others Houſes, moſt of which were thoſe of the prime Actors in that Profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord's Day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1634, On a Lord's Day, in the time of a great Froſt, Fourteen young Men while they were playing at Foot-ball upon the Ice on the River <hi>Trent,</hi> near to <hi>Gain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>borough,</hi> meeting all together in a ſcuffle, the Ice ſuddenly broke, and they were all drowned.</p>
               <p>In the Edg of <hi>Eſſex</hi> near <hi>Brinckly,</hi> two Fellows working in a Chalk-Pit, the one was boaſting to his Companion how he had angred his Miſtreſs with ſtaying ſo late at their Sports the laſt Sunday Night, but he ſaid he would anger her worſe the next Sunday Night; but he had no ſooner ſaid
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49981:48"/>
this, but ſuddenly the Earth fell down upon him, and kill'd him outright, with the Fall whereof his Fellow's Limbs was broken, who had been alſo Partner with him in his Jollity on the Lord's Day.</p>
               <p>In the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> one <hi>Edward Ameridith</hi> a Gentleman, being pained in his Feet a long time, and being ſomewhat recovered, one ſaid to him he was glad to ſee him ſo nimble, Mr. <hi>Ameridith</hi> replied, he doubted not but to dance about the May-Pole the next Lord's Day, but before he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of that place he was ſmitten with ſuch a Feebleneſs of Heart, and Diſſineſs in his Head, that deſiring help to carry him to a Houſe, he died be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the next Lord's Day came.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Walton</hi> in <hi>Surrey</hi> upon the <hi>Thames,</hi> there in a great Froſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 1634, Three young Men on the Lord's Day, after they had been at the Church in the Forenoon, where the Miniſter preſſing the words of his Text, out of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>That we muſt all appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. They the while whiſpered as they ſate: And in the Afternoon they went together over the <hi>Thames</hi> upon the Ice, unto a diſorderly Houſe of Gameing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where they ſpent the remainder of the Lord's Day, and part of the Night alſo in Revelling; one of them in a Tavern merrily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing the next Day of his Sabbath Deeds, and of his Voyage over the Ice; but on the Tuſday after theſe three returning homewards, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to paſs over the Ice again, they all ſunk down to the bottom like Stones; whereof one only was miraculouſly preſerved, but the other two were drowned.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49981:48"/>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1598, the Town of <hi>Teverton</hi> in <hi>Devo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhire,</hi> was often warned and adviſed, and told by the Godly Paſtor thereof, that God would bring ſome heavy Judgment upon the Inhabitants of that place, for their horrible Profanation of the Lord's Day, occaſioned chiefly by reaſon of their Market-day being on the Monday, and accordingly not long after their Miniſter's death, in the ſaid Year, God ſent a terrible Fire, which in leſs then half an Hour conſumed the whole Town; except the Church, the Court-houſe, Almes-houſes, and a few poor People's Dwellings, and above 50 Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were conſumed and periſhed in the Flames. Alſo <hi>Anno</hi> 1612, it was again wholly burnt down, except a few poor Houſes; they not being warned by the former Judgment, but continuing in the ſame Sin.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1635, A Profane Company of young Men went (as Mr. <hi>Faucnor</hi> relates) on the Lord's Day early in the Morning to <hi>Clarendon-Park,</hi> to cut down a May-Pole, and having loaden the Cart with it, at <hi>Miln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs-Barn</hi> entring into <hi>Salisbury,</hi> one of the Cart Wheels falling into a Rutt, made the young Tree in the Cart (which they had ſtoln for a Pole) to give a great ſhugg on one ſide, which ſtruck one of the Company ſuch a blow on the Head, that it beat out his Brains, ſo that he preſently died in the place, and there lay a fearful Spectacle of God's Wrath, both againſt that idle Sport, and wilful proſaning of the Sabbath, whilſt he makes the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing they had choſen for their Sport and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, to be the Inſtrument of executing his Fury. And Dr. <hi>Teate</hi> gives a ſecond Example of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in the Year 1626.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:49981:49"/>
We read that Mr. <hi>Abberley</hi> a Godly Miniſter in <hi>Burton</hi> upon <hi>Trent,</hi> did often take occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and threaten Sabbath-breakers, eſpecially ſuch as ſold and bought Meat upon the Sabbath-day Mornings, a Practice too common it ſeems in that place; nevertheleſs there was a Taylor in the Town, a very nimble active Fellow, dwelling at the upper end of the Town, who would go through the long Street (as it were in Bravado) to the other end of the Town, and fetch home Meat on the Lord's Day before Morning-Prayer: But as he came back with both his Hands full, in the midſt of the Street he fell down ſtark dead, which as it pleaſed God, ſays the Doctor, did work ſome Reformation, both amongſt the Butchers and others. When I was in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> (ſays my Author) there was one Sir <hi>T. S.</hi> a Papiſt, and at that time in favour at the Court, who coming into his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was much feaſted and followed by the Gentry, and upon a Sabbath day was entertained and feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at a Knight's Houſe, where many others were preſent; towards Evening they went to Dancing, and in the midſt of their Sports there was one Sir <hi>J. D.</hi> that had a great Blow given him on his Leg, by an inviſible Hand, which made him lame for a long time after.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Savage</hi> (a young Man who was Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Ratcliff, Octob.</hi> 28. 1668, for Murthering his Fellow-Servant) whilſt he was in <hi>Newgate,</hi> cryed out thus to ſome that came to ſee him, <hi>O Wretch</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtudied how I might ſpend the Lord's Day in the Devil's Work, I thought I could never diſhonour God enough, and that time I ſhould have ſerved God in, I did moſt for Satan in it; on the</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:49981:49"/>
                  <hi>Sabbaths I uſed to play my Prancks, I ſometimes went into the Church indeed, but (I may ſpeak it to my Shame and deep Sorrow) I never heard one whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon all the while I was with my Maſter, and indeed I laughed at thoſe that ſpent the Sabbath in Hearing and Praying, and looked upon them as the verieſt Fools in the World; I was glad when the Sabbath came, that I might have time to run to my Vile Comrades, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiced that then I could go to ſatisfy my curſed Luſts with Wheriſh Women. O tell young Men from me, that the breaking of the Sabbath is a dangerous and coſtly Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo while he, was in <hi>Newgate,</hi> one Sabbath day his Fellow-Priſoners being at Cards, asked him to join with them, <hi>O</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you and I have ſomething elſe to do with our Time, than to play at Cards; is it now a time for us to be ſporting away the Sabbath, when we have but one poor Sand left us to work for Eternity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Miniſter on a time preaching and preſſing the Sanctification of the Sabbath, had occaſion in his Sermon to make mention of that Man, that by the ſpecial Command of God was ſtoned to death for gathering Sticks upon the Sabbath day. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon one in the Congregation ſtood up and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and made all the haſte that he could out of the Church, and went to gathering of Sticks, the he had no need of them, but when the People came out from Sermon they found this Man ſtark dead, with the bundle of Sticks in his Arms, lying in the Church-Porch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory Tomonenſis</hi> reports, that an Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who upon the Lord's Day went to plow his Field, as he cleanſed his Plow-ſhare with an Iron,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49981:50"/>
the Iron ſtuck ſo faſt into his Hand, that for two Years he could not be delivered from it, but carried it about continually to his exceeding great Pain and Shame.</p>
               <p>Another Profane Fellow without any regard to God or his Service, made no Conſcience to lead his Corn out of the Field on the Lord's Day in Sermon time; but he was well rewarded for his ungodly Covetouſneſs, for that Corn which with ſo much care he gathered together, was conſumed with Fire from Heaven, with the Barn, and all the Grain that was in it.</p>
               <p>And a certain Noble-man every Lord's Day uſing to go a Hunting in the Sermon time, the Lord puniſhed his Impiety with this Judgment, he cauſed his Lady to bring forth a Child with a Head like a Dog, that ſeeing he preſerred his Dogs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Service of God, he might have one of his own getting, to make much of.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Kimſtat</hi> a Town in <hi>France,</hi> in the Year 1559, there lived a certain covetous Women that was ſo greedy of Gain, that ſhe would neither frequent the Church her ſelf to hear the Word of God, not ſuffer any of her Family to go, but continually ſtay'd labouring and toyling about drying and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Flax, and doing other domeſtick Buſineſſes, and could not be reclaimed by her Neighbours, and one Sabbath day Fire ſeemed to run among the Flax without doing any harm, the next Sabbath day it took Fire indeed, but was quickly extinct; all this would give her no warning, but ſhe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued obſtinate in her Profaneneſs, the third Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day the Flax again taking Fire could not be quenched, till it burnt her, and two of her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49981:50"/>
to death; for tho they were taken out alive, yet the next day they all three died, and that which was moſt to be wondered at (ſays the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter) a young Infant in the Cradle was taken out of the mid'ſt of the Flames without any hurt: thus God uſes to exerciſe his Judgments upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of his Commandments.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1583, at <hi>London,</hi> at the <hi>Bear-Garden,</hi> a great number of People being gathered together on a Sabbath day to ſee the Sport, the Lord that he might chaſten them in ſome ſort, and ſhow his diſlike of the profaning the Sabbath. cauſed the Scaffolds ſuddenly to break; the Beholders to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble down headlong, ſo that eight Perſons Men and Women were ſlain, beſides many others were ſore hurt and bruifed, to the ſhorthing of their Lives.</p>
               <p>The like Judgment happened at a Town in <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire</hi> called <hi>Riſley,</hi> in the Year 1607, where the Floor of a Chamber, wherein a great number were gathered together to ſee a Play on the Sabbath day, fell down, and many by the Fall thereof ſore hurt, and ſome killed.</p>
               <p>In <hi>May</hi> 1629, one <hi>John Bow</hi> of <hi>Ely</hi> (Coachman to one Mr. <hi>Batnum</hi> of <hi>Beenham)</hi> a Fellow very vitious, and exceeding in theſe two Evils of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Swearing and Drunkenneſs, on the Sabbath day in the Sermon time drank himſelf drunk, ſo that when he was to ſit in the Coach-box to drive the Coach, he fell from it under the Horſes Feet, and was trodden to death, or ſo hurt at leaſt that he died ſhortly after.</p>
               <p>In <hi>November</hi> 1621, one <hi>Richard Burn</hi> Servant to <hi>Jaſper Burch,</hi> Gardiner of <hi>Ely,</hi> accuſtomed to travel on the Lord's Day, and making no reckoning of the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49981:51"/>
Sabbath, ſeldom or never coming to the Church on that day but went onwards to St. <hi>Ives Market,</hi> and ſo ſpent the day; and being drunk, was at length overtaken by the juſt Judgment of God, for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Stream in his Boat, which he had loaden with Marketable Wares, he fell into the River and was drowned.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hugh Clark,</hi> preaching about <hi>Oundle</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> where the People were general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very ignorant, and much addicted to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of the Lord's Day, by <hi>Whitſon-Ales,</hi> Maurice-Dances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he much ſet himſelf againſt, endeavouring to evince their, and to draw them from the Evil and Danger o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Sin, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing God's Judgments in caſe of their obſtinate Perſeverance: but they being train'd up in thoſe Courſes, and hardned by cuſtom, perſiſted ſtill in their Wickedneſs. At laſt on a Lord's Day the Leader of the Dance, a Luſty young Man, in the mid'ſt of their Profane Paſtimes, fell down ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and died; but they ſoon ſhaking off their Fear, returned to their Vomit again; the Lord's Day following Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> took occaſion from this ſad diſpenſation to quote that Text, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 27. <hi>If thou wilt not hearken to me, to hallow the Sabbath day,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then will I kindle a Fire in the Gates thereof,</hi> &amp;c. The People ſtill kick'd againſt theſe Admonitions, and the Eve following returned to their Sports a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, among whom was a Smith that was a chief Ring-leader, but it pleaſed God the very next day, two Husbandmen coming to ſharpen their Plow-ſhares at his Shop, a ſpark from the red hot Iron as he was beating it upon the Anvil, flew into the Thatch, which both the Smith and the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49981:51"/>
ſaw, but had no power to move towards it, which preſently burnt down the Shop, Houſe, and all the Smith had. This Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> preſſed upon their Conſciences, but nothing would prevail till at laſt upon a Sabbath day at Night, when they were return'd to their ſeveral Homes, there was heard a great noiſe and ratling of Chains up and down the Town, which was accompanied with ſuch a ſmell and ſtink of Fire and Brimſtone, that many of their guilty Conſciences ſuggeſted to them that the Devil was come to fetch them away quick into Hell, and now and not till now they began to think in good earneſt of a Reformation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edmond Kirke</hi> Vintner, executed <hi>July</hi> 11. 1684, for murthering his Wife, in his Confeſſion acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged himſelf frequently guilty of profaning the Lord's Day, upon which Holy Day (ſaith he) I committed the heinous Sin of murthering my Wife. Thus Sin was puniſhed with Sin, a leſs with a greater, and the greater with the Gallows, and that greater committed near the ſame Gallows, and himſelf confeſſed that he had (to his Wife asking whilſt ſhe paſſed by what place that was) told her, it was <hi>Tyburn,</hi> where <hi>John Gower</hi> was lately hang'd for killing his Wife. <hi>O Lord how dear to me thy Counſels are, but how juſt and terrible thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Smythies</hi> Curate of St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s <hi>Cripple-gate,</hi> in the Confeſſion and Diſcovery of a condemned Priſoner executed for Theft, <hi>May</hi> 25, 1687, ſaith (as Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> reports) that it was his earneſt deſire that all young Men ſhould take care not to miſpend the Lord's Day. And I do not know (ſays Mr. <hi>Smythies)</hi> that ever I obſerved any Repentance in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49981:52"/>
a condemned Malefactor, who did not bitterly lament his neglect of his duty to God on that day.</p>
               <p>In a Convocation of the Clergy at <hi>Perth</hi> in <hi>Scotland, Anno</hi> 1188, for the better Sanctification of the Sabbath day; it was ordained (as Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Spotſwood</hi> tells us) that every Saturday from twelve of the Clock ſhould be ſet apart for prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereunto, and that all People at the ſound of the Bell ſhould addreſs themſelves to hear Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and abſtain from worldly Labours till Monday Morning.</p>
               <p>If nothing that is here ſhewed can prevail, or any ways induce the preſumptuous obſtinate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaners of the Lord's Day to forſake their ſinful and provoking Wickedneſs, then let him that is young obſerve what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Rejoice O young Man in thy Youth, and let thy Heart chear thee in the days of thy Youth, and walk in the ways of thy Heart, and in the ſight of thine Eyes. But know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee into Judgment,</hi> Eccleſ. 11. 9. <hi>And he that is old, let him know that death is at his Heels, ready to trip them up, and gives no warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his coming; let not ſuch an one therefore procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and put off Repentance, but let him watch, for he knows neither the day nor the hour wherein the Son of Man cometh. For he ſhall come in an hour that he is not aware of, and if he find him in the daring provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purſuit of his unrepented of Prafaneſs, ſhall cut him in ſunder, and appoint him his Portion with the Hypocrites, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi> Math. 24. 50, 51. and 25. 13. <hi>Luke.</hi> 12. 46.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:49981:52"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A brief Account of the Laws made againſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and debauched Men, and lew'd Women, about getting Baſtards.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOte that before the Raign of K. <hi>H.</hi> 7. there were eighteen infamous Stews or Brothel-houſes, and <hi>H.</hi> 7. for a time forbad them; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards twelve only were permitted, and had Signs painted on their Walls, as a Boars-Head, the Croſs-Keys, the Gun, the Caſtle, the Cardinals-Hat, the Bell, the Swan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But afterwards <hi>H.</hi> 8. in the 37<hi>th</hi> Year of his Raign, by Proclamation under the great Seal, dated 30 <hi>March, Anno</hi> 37. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſuppreſſed all the Stews and Brothel-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on the Bank-ſide in <hi>Southwark,</hi> for that they were againſt the Law of God, and the Law of the Land: And thoſe Infamous, Women were not bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in Chriſtian Burial, when they were dead, nor permitted to receive the Rites of the Church whilſt they lived.</p>
               <p>And the Keeper, He or She, of ſuch Houſes, is puniſhable by Indictment at the Common Law, by Fine and Impriſonment; for altho Adultery and Fornication be puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſtical Law, yet the keeping of Bawdy, or Stews, or Brothel-houſes, being as it were a Common Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, is puniſhable by the Common Law, and is the cauſe of-many Miſchiefs, not only to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of their Bodies, but to the indangering of their Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:49981:53"/>
By the Cuſtom of <hi>London,</hi> as appears by the 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>Fol.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If a Conſtable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> has Notice that a Woman is in Adultery with a Man, that a Man or Woman of Evil Fame, is gone to a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Houſe, he may take help with him and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Houſe, and if he find them ſo, he may ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt them, and carry them to Priſon, or to a Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Peace, to be bound over and proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>Baſtards begotten and born out of lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, being an Offence againſt God's Law, and Man's Law.</p>
               <p>It is by the Statute 18 <hi>Eliz. Chap.</hi> 3. Enacted, <q>That two Juſtices of the Peace, whereof one to be of the Quorum, in or next to the Limits where the Pariſh Church is, within which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh a Baſtard ſhall be born, that may be charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Pariſh (upon Examination of the Cauſe and Circumſtances) ſhall by their diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion take order, as well for the puniſhment of the Mother and reputed Father, of ſuch Baſtard Child, as alſo for the relief of every ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in part, or in all; and for the keeping of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch Baſtard Child; by charging ſuch Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or reputed Father, with the Payment of Money weekly, or other Suſtentation for the relief of ſuch Child in ſuch wiſe as they ſhall think meet and convenient. And if after the ſame Order by them ſubſcribed under their Hands, the Mother or reputed Father upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, ſhall not obſerve and perform the ſame, that then every ſuch Party ſo making Default in the non-performance thereof, to be committed to the Common Goal without Bail,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49981:53"/>
except they give ſufficient Surety to perform the ſame, or to appear Perſonally at the next Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seſſions of the Peace to be holden for the ſame County, where ſuch Order ſhall be taken, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to abide ſuch Order, as the Juſtices there, or the more part of them, ſhall take in that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half (if they take any) and if they take none at the Seſſions, then to abide and perform the Order before made as is aboveſaid.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And by the Statute 7 <hi>Jas.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 4. It is Enacted, <q>That every lewd Woman which ſhall have any Baſtard Child, which may be charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Pariſh, the Juſtice of Peace ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch lewd Woman to the Houſe of Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there to be puniſhed, and ſet on work du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the term of one whole Year; and if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhe offend again, then to be committed to the Houſe of Correction as aforeſaid, and to remain there, until ſhe can put in good Sureties for her good Behaviour, not to offend ſo again.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And by the Statute 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 4. It is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, <q>That all Juſtices of the Peace, within their ſeveral Limits and Precincts, and in their ſeveral Seſſions, may do and execute all things concerning that part of the Statute 18 <hi>Eliz. Ch.</hi> 3. aforementioned, that by Juſtices of the Peace in the ſeveral Counties are by the ſaid Statute li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to be done.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Puniſhment appointed by theſe Statutes being gentle and eaſy, we ſee by every days Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that Baſtards are very frequently begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; I ſhall therefore inform ſuch vitious profane and ſinful Perſons in the next Chapter, what Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments the Scripture has appointed for ſuch
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49981:54"/>
Perſons of ſuch profligate and debauched Lives, that they may not be ignorant of the great Anger and Diſpleaſure conceived by Almighty God againſt ſuch profane ſinful Courſes, and of the great Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and Danger they involve their precious Souls in, if they forſake not their vitious way of living, and by hearty Repentance cleanſe their Souls, <hi>putting away the Filth of the Fleſh,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 3. 21. And <hi>perfecting Holineſs in the Fear of God.</hi> 2 Cor. 7. 1. <hi>For he that ſoweth to the Fleſh, ſhall of the Fleſh reap Corruption<hi>:</hi> but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit neap Life everlaſting.</hi> Gal. 6. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the ſeveral Places of Scripture threatning Judgments, or forbidding Adultery, Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Incontinency, Laſoiviouſneſs and Whoredom, and ſhewing God's Anger and Diſpleaſure againſt ſuch profane Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <q>THou ſhalt not commit Adultery. <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 14.</bibl> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Do not proſtitute thy Daughter, to cauſe her to be a VV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re; leſt the Land fall to VVhoredom, and the Land become full of VVickedneſs. <bibl>
                        <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 29.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that committeth Adultery with another Mans VVife, even he that committeth Adultery with his Neighbours VVife, the and the Adultereſs ſhall ſurely put to death, <bibl>
                        <hi>Lev.</hi> 20. 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49981:54"/>
                  <q>And the Daughter of any Prieſt, if ſhe profane her ſelf by playing the Whore, ſhe profaneth her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhe ſhall be hurnt with Fire. <bibl>
                        <hi>Levit.</hi> 21. 9.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>If a Man be found lying with a Woman married to an Husband, then they ſhall both of them die, both the Man that lay with the VVoman, and the VVoman: So ſhalt thou put away Evil from <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 22.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Eye alſo of the Adulterer waiteth for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, ſaying, No Eye ſhall ſee me, and diſg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſeth his Face. <bibl>
                        <hi>Job</hi> 24. 15.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>VVhen thou ſaweſt a Thief thou conſented'ſt unto him, and haſt been Partaker with the Adulterers. <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>By the means of a VVhoriſh VVoman, a Man is brought to a piece of Bread, and the Adultereſs will hunt for the precious Life. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 26.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Who ſo committeth Adultery with a VVoman, lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding: He that doth it, deſtroyeth his own Soul. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 32.</bibl>
                  </q> 
                  <q>A VVound and Diſhonour ſhall he get, and his Reproach ſhall not be wiped away. <bibl>
                        <hi>ver.</hi> 33.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Lips of a ſtrange VVoman drop as an Honey-Comb, and her Mouth is ſmoother than Oil. But her and is bitter as Worm-wood, ſharp as a two-edged Sword, her Feet go down to death, her Steps take hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Hell. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 5. 3, 4, 5. <hi>and</hi> 2. 18. <hi>and</hi> 7. 27.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>A Whore is a deep Ditch; and a ſtrange Women <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>a narrow Pit. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.27. <hi>and</hi> 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. Such i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the way of an Adulterous Woman; ſhe eateth and wipeth her Mouth, and ſaith, I have done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Wickedneſs. <bibl>
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>O that I had in the Wilderneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lodging Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> Way-faring Men, that I might leave my People, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49981:55"/>
go from them; for they be all Adulterers, an Aſſembly of Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acherous Men. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Will ye ſteal, murder, commit Adultery, and ſwear falſly, and burn In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence unto <hi>Baal,</hi> and walk after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gods whom ye know not. Therefore I will caſt you out of my ſight. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 9, 15.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I have ſeen thine Adulteries, and thy Neighings, the lewdneſs of thy Whoredom, and thine Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Fields; We unto thee, O <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> wilt thou not be made clean; when ſhall it once be? <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 27.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Becauſe they have committed Villany in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and have committed Adultery with their Neighbours Wives, and have ſpoken lying words in my Name, which I have not commanded them, even I know, and am a Witneſs ſaith the Lord. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 29. 23.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For the Land is full of Adulteries, for becauſe of ſwearing the Land mourneth: The pleaſant Places of the VVilderneſs are dried up, and their Courſe is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and their Force is not Right. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In thee have they diſcovered their Fathers Nakedneſs; in thee have they humbled her that was ſet apart for Pollution. And one hath committed Abomination with his Neighbours Wife, and another hath lewdly defiled his Daughter in Law, and another in thee hath humbled his Siſter, his Father's Daughter. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 10, 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>By Swearing, and Lying, and Killing, and Steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and committing Adultery, they broke out, and Blood to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cheth Blood. Therefore ſhall the Land mourn, and every one that dwelleth therein ſhall languiſh. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whoredom and Wine, and New Wine take away the Heart. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 11.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:49981:55"/>
                  <q>I will not puniſh your Daughters when they commit Whoredom, nor your Spouſes when they commit Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery: for themſelves are ſeparated with Whores, and they ſacrifice with Harlots; therefore the People that doth not underſtand, ſhall fall. <bibl>
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 14.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I will come near unto you, to Judgment, and I will be a ſwift Witneſs againſt the Sorcerers, and againſt the Adulterers. <bibl>
                        <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 5.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>A Fornicator in the Body of his Fleſh, will never ceaſe till he hath kindled a Fire. All Bread is ſweet to a Whoremonger, he will not leave off till he die. A Man that breaketh Wedlock, ſaying thus in his Heart, Who ſeeth me? I am compaſſed about with darkneſs, the Walls cover me, and no Body ſeeth me, what need I to fear, the moſt High will not remember my Sins? Such a Man only feareth the Eyes of Men, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that the Eyes of the Lord are ten thouſand times brighter than the Sun, beholding all the ways of Men, and conſidering the moſt ſecret parts. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 23. 16, 17, 18, 19.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thus ſhall it go with the Wife that leaveth her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and bringeth in an Heir by another. She ſhall leave her Memory to be curſed, and her Reproach ſhall not be blotted out. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 23. 22, 26.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Three ſorts of Men my Soul hateth, and I am great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended at their Life; a Poor Man that is proud, a Rich Man that is a Lyar, and an Old Adulterer that doteth. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 25. 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Whoredom of a Woman may be known in her haughty Looks and Eye-lids. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 26. 9.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Be aſhamed of Whoredom before Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of a Lye before a Prince and a mighty Man. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 41. 18.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But I ſay unto you, whoſoever looketh on a Woman to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49981:56"/>
luſt after her, hath committed Adultery with her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in his Heart. <bibl>
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 28.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Out of the Heart proceed Evil Thoughts, Murders, Adulteries, Fornications, Thefts, falſe Witneſs, Blaſphemies. <bibl>
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 19.</bibl> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 7. 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But that we write unto them, that they abſtain from Pollutions of Idols, and from Fornication, and from things ſtrangled, and from Blood. <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 20.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>God gave them over to a Reprobate Mind, to do thoſe things which are not convenient: Being filled with all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, Fornication, Wickedneſs, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Maliciouſneſs; full of Envy, Murder, Debate, Deceit, Malignity, Wiſperers. <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 28, 29.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I wrote to you in an Epiſtle, not to company with Fornicators. <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 9.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Know ye not, that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God. Be not deceived, neither Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, nor Abuſers of themſelves with Mankind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Revilers, nor Extortioners ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God. <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Meats for the Belly, and the Belly for Meats, but God ſhall diſtroy both it and them. Now the Body is not for Fornication, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the Body. <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 13.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Neither let us commit Fornication, as ſome of them did, and fell in one day three and twenty thouſand. <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 8.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Having therefore theſe Promiſes (dearly Beloved) let us cleanſe our ſelves from all Filthineſs of the Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting Holineſs in the Fear of God. <bibl>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:49981:56"/>
                  <q>Now the works of the Fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe, Adultery, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in time paſt, that they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God. <bibl>
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 19, 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Who being paſt feeling, have given themſelves over unto Laſciviouſneſs, to work all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 19.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But Fornication, and all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, or Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, let it not be once named amongst you, as becometh Saints: Neither Filthineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For this ye know, that no Whoremonger, unclean Perſon, nor coverous Man who is an Idolater, hath any Inheritance in the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of God. <bibl>
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 3, 5.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Mortify therefore your Members which are upon the Earth, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, inordinate Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, evil Concupiſcence, and Covetouſneſs which is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. For which things ſake the Wrath of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on the Children of Diſobedience. <bibl>
                        <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 5, 6.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For this is the Will of God, even your Sanctification, that ye ſhould abſtain from Fornication; that every one of you ſhould know how to poſſeſs his Veſſel in San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and Honour, not in the Luſt of Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, as the Gentiles which knew not God. <bibl>1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 3, 4, 5.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Knowing this, that the Law is not made for a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man, but for Whoremongers, for them that defile themſelves with Mankind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <bibl>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 9, 10.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Leſt there be any Fornicator, or profane Perſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Eſau,</hi> who for one morſel of Meat ſold his Birth-right. <bibl>
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 16.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Marriage is honourable in all, and the Bed undefiled: but Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judg. <bibl>
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:49981:57"/>
                  <q>Wherefore lay aſide all Filthineſs, and ſuperſluity of Naughtineſs, and receive with Meekneſs the engrafied Word, which is able to ſave your Souls. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 21.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Ye Adulterers and Adultereſſes, know ye not that the Friendſhip of the World, is Enmity with God? <bibl>
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 4.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Having Eyes full of Adultery, and that cannot ceaſe from Sin, beguiling unſtable Souls. <bibl>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 14.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>For all that is in the World, the Luſt of the Fleſh, and the Luſt of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life, is not of the Father, but of the World. <bibl>1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 16.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Even as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> and the Cities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, in like manner giving themſelves over to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and going after ſtrange Fleſh, are ſet forth for an Example, ſuffering the Vengeance of Eternal Fire. <bibl>
                        <hi>Jude ver.</hi> 7.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But the fearful, and unbelieving, and abominable, and Muderers, and Wboremongers, and Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and all Liars, ſhall have their part in the Lake which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone: which is the ſecond Death. <bibl>
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 8.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>More Places of Scripture might be cited to this purpoſe, but I ſuppoſe theſe may be ſufficient to convince any ſober rational Chriſtian of the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that attend the ſinful Wickedneſs of inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency and Whoring. I ſhall therefore proceed to the next Chapter, and acquaint the Reader with ſome few ſignal Marks of God's Juſtice in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Perſons guilty of ſuch profane Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and ſo ſhall conclude this Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:49981:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>An Account of ſome Perſons ſignally puniſhed by Almighty God for the Profane and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Vice of Whoring, and Luſtful Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE read in Scripture that the <hi>Sons of</hi> Ely <hi>were Sons of</hi> Belial, <hi>they knew not the Lord. And when their Father heard all that his Sons did unto all</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and how they lay with the Women that aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the Door of the Tabernacle of the Congregation;</hi> Their Father <hi>Ely</hi> reprov'd them, ſaying, <hi>ye make the Lord's People to tranſgreſs. If one Man ſin againſt another, the Judg ſhall judg him; but if a Man ſin againſt the Lord, who ſhall intreat for him? Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they hearkned not to the Voice of their Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord would ſlay them.</hi> Which accordingly came to paſs: For the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> fighting againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> made a great Slaughter of them, <hi>for there fell of</hi> Iſrael <hi>thirty thouſand Footmen. And the Ark of God was taken, and the two Sons of</hi> Eli, Hophni <hi>and</hi> Phineas <hi>were ſlain.</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 12, 22, 24, 25. and 4. 10, 11.</p>
               <p>And <hi>David</hi> having committed Adultery with <hi>Bathſheba</hi> the Wife of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and cauſed her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to be ſlain: The Lord thereupon cauſed <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom David</hi>'s own Son, to rebel againſt him, ſo that he was forced to flie from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for foar of his Son, and had his Head covered, and went bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, and wept when he went up by the Aſcent of Mount <hi>Olivet:</hi> As appears by the Story, in the 2 <hi>Sam. Ch.</hi> 11. and 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:49981:58"/>
In <hi>Germany</hi> a Gentleman of Note, finding his Wife in Bed with another Man, ſlew firſt the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, and then his own Wife.</p>
               <p>A Nobleman in <hi>Thuringia</hi> being taken in Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, the Husband of the Adultereſs bound him Hand and Foot, caſt him into Priſon, kept him faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, only cauſing daily hot Diſhes of Meat to be ſet before him, to tantalize him with the ſmell: in this Torture the Letcher continued till he gnawed off the Fleſh from his own Shoulders, and on the eleventh day he died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> Wife to the Emperor <hi>Otho</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> carry'd a young Fornicatour along with her in Womans Habit: But he being diſcovered was burnt to death. Afterwards ſoliciting the Count of <hi>Mutina,</hi> and not able to draw him to her Lure, ſhe accuſed him to the Emperor, of attempting a Rape upon her, for which he was Beheaded: But the Emperor at laſt finding out his Wife's Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, cauſed her to be burnt at a Stake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> tells us of a great Man in his Country, ſo beſotted with the Sin of Whoredom, that he was not aſhamed to ſay, that if he might live for ever here, and be carried from one Whore-houſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, there to ſatisfy his Luſts, he would never deſire any other Heaven; this Vile Fellow after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards breathed out his wretched Soul betwixt two notorious Harlots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joan</hi> Queen of <hi>Naples</hi> was inſatiable for her Luſt, which cauſed her to hang her firſt Husband (which was <hi>Andrew,</hi> ſecond Son to the King of <hi>Hungary)</hi> at her Window, for inſufficiency. Her ſecond Husband was <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Tarentum</hi> who died with the over-ſtraining himſelf to ſatisfy her Luſtful
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49981:58"/>
Appetite. Her third Husband <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Tarracon,</hi> a gallant Gentleman, ſhe Beheaded, for lying with another Woman. Her fourth Husband was <hi>Otho</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> in whoſe time the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> drew her out of her Kingdom, and having taken her, hung her out of the ſame Window, where ſhe had hang'd her firſt Husband.</p>
               <p>An ancient Gentleman of good Account, marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a beautiful young Gentlewoman, but having no Iſſue, he took into his Houſe a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a Neighbours Son, and compleatly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, purpoſing to make him a ſharer in his Eſtate. This Gentleman grows familiar with his Wife, which gave ſo much occaſion of Suſpicion, and caus'd ſuch a Rumour in the Country, that his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requires him to return home again: He doth ſo, but at parting, promiſeth Marriage to the Gentlewoman, in caſe of her Old Husbands de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, and ſhe to him, both with Oaths. The Old Gentleman's Maid meeting with this young Gallant over a Glaſs of Wine, tells him in private, how much his Company was miſſed at her Maſter's Houſe, and his Return deſired. But withal, tho ſhe knew the Familiarities between him and her Miſtreſs, yet it was all feigned, for another en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed both her Heart and Body (naming the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon); the Gentleman is ſtartled, but incredulous. And after ſome time the Old Gentleman ſends for him again; he goes in the Night, but very privily (having before by Letter deſired that the Garden Door might be left open for him) and tells the Old Gentleman the reaſon of his abſence: But before he went back, he goes ſoftly to the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman's Bed-chamber Door (who often lay by
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49981:59"/>
her ſelf) and hears the Whiſpers of two diſtinct Voices. Upon which in a ſudden Paſſion, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to break in upon them, and run them through with a Sword; but relenting with tenderneſs, he departs ſoftly to his own home, grows melancholy and diſtemper'd; but recovering, he reſolved to travel. The Old Gentleman ſends for him to take an unwilling Farewel: At the importunity of his Father he goes. After Dinner the Gentlewoman ſingles him out for a Farewel, weeping in his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and beſeeching him to have care of his Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but eſpecially of his Vow and Promiſe. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Reply, he gave her a Letter, which he deſired her to peruſe in his Abſence. She opens the Letter, and reads there all the Story of her Luſt laid open, particularly and pathetically. This ſtruck her to the Heart. She falling preſently into Frenzy and Deſpairing, ſoon after died: Which News came to the Gentleman before he reach'd <hi>Graveſend.</hi> The Old Man afterwards inriched him with a great part of his Land, which he enjoys (ſaith my Author) to this day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Savage</hi> frequenting the Houſe of <hi>Hannah Blan,</hi> a noted Bawdy-Houſe, ſpending upon her ſuch Money as he could get, to ſatisfy his own Luſt and her craving Appetite, is tempted firſt to ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and purloining from his Maſter, and at length to the murthering of a Maid, his Fellow-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; for which he was afterwards brought to the Gallows and hang'd.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Robert Foulks</hi> of <hi>Stanton Lacy,</hi> firſt an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, and then a Murtherer of his Baſtard Child, ended his Days very Ignominiouſly at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> tho Penitently.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49981:59"/>
                  <hi>John Allerion</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Waterford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for unnatural Concupiſcence, came to a very diſgraceful end, being arraigned and executed at <hi>Dublin</hi> for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Venery was the Deſtruction of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, of <hi>Otho</hi> the Emperor (call'd for his good parts otherwiſe, <hi>Miraculum mundi)</hi> of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> 4. who died of a Wicked Waſte; of <hi>Paul</hi> the 4th, of whom it paſſed for a Proverb, <hi>Enim per eandem partem animam profudiſſe, per quam acceperat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis notoriouſly known, how far this Sin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed in <hi>England,</hi> amongſt the lazy Monks and Nuns, what Skulls of Infants were found near their Religious Houſes, before the diſſolution of them in <hi>K. H.</hi> 8. days: And much about the ſame time, <hi>viz.</hi> at the beginning of the Reformation (as I have read in a Letter writ by the Popes Notary to a Gentleman of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſays my Author) there was a Nunnery viſited in the Outer Skirts of <hi>Italy,</hi> and thirteen of the Nuns found with Child at the ſame time, all by the Confeſſor, for which cauſe by order of the Pope it was put down.</p>
               <p>The Miniſter of <hi>Staunton Lacy,</hi> Mr. <hi>Foulk</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, who was executed at <hi>Tyburn, Jan.</hi> 31. 1678, for murdering his Baſtard-Child: being at the place of Execution, he admoniſhed the People to conſider the Miſchief of Uncleanneſs; and what a Sin it was, for a Member of Chriſt to make himſelf the Member of an Harlot; that it was a Sin that ſeldom goes alone, but is the Mother-Sin to a number more; warning all to avoid the Snares of a Whoriſh Woman, and to keep the Marriage-Bed undefiled, and to remember his Ignominious <hi>Exit,</hi> occaſioned by his ſinful defiling of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:49981:60"/>
                  <hi>Nathaniel Butler,</hi> executed in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1657, for killing his Fellow-Prentice; being at the place of Execution, he warned the People to beware of the Beginning of Sin, ſaying, <hi>When I was firſt enticed into Evil, I was tender and fearful of it; but not diligently hearkning to the Word of God, nor the Voice and Checks of Conſcience, I went on ſo, that by degrees I was emboldned in Sin, and at laſt it became as familiar to me as my daily Food. Therefore as you love your Souls, take heed of the beginnings of Sin: If I had ſo done, I had eſcaped this Puniſhment and Shameful end. O that I could prevail</hi> (cry'd he) <hi>with every young Perſon to caſt away Sin betimes, and check it in the firſt beginning; and that I had taken the Counſel which I have now given,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Loathing my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved and Darling-Sin <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs:</hi> And admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all young People to watch and pray againſt it. Hoping if he were to live as many Years, as he had then but Moments to live, he ſhould (through the Grace of God) never commit it any more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Marketman,</hi> executed in <hi>Eſſex</hi> for murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Wife, <hi>April</hi> 17. 1680, confeſſed he had departed from his God in his Youth; that he had neglected the Church and the publick Worſhip of God, and chooſing rather to ſpend his time in an Ale-houſe: It brought me (ſays he) to Evil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſo to Drunkenneſs; which getting an habit made me a profeſſed Enemy to God, and to give my ſelf over to Swearing and Curſing, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Whoring, and ſo from one Sin to another, till I arrived at the height of all Impiety, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That formerly he loved to commit Sin, but now hated the very thoughts of it, and would not commit a Sin for a Kingdom; exhorting the People to take
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49981:60"/>
heed of the beginnings of Sin, telling them you will find if once you habituate your ſelves to the committing of Sin, it will be very hard to root it out: it muſt coſt you many a Tear, and much Bitterneſs in crucifying your Darling-Sins: which Trouble and Expence might be ſav'd, if you would be careful to reſiſt the firſt Temptation. Bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Drunkenneſs and Uncleanneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry Parker</hi> Executed at <hi>Tyburn</hi> 1689, for Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting Guineas, lamented much the miſpending of his Time, ſaying, <hi>O the precious Time I have ſquandered away upon Trifles and Vanities, upon my Luſts and Pleaſures, which I now want to make my Peace with God, and purchaſe Eternal Life! That it was not ſo eaſy to repent as he ſuppoſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were endleſs to enumerate all the ſad Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Divine Judgments that might be brought under this Head, but I ſhall not multiply Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but recommend theſe already ſet down, to the peruſal and ſerious Conſideration of all profane, laſcivious, incontinent, debauched Perſons, and ſhall conclude and ſhut up all in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Adviſe to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 13, 14. <hi>Let us walk honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as in the day, not in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strife and Envying. But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make no Proviſion for the Fleſh to fulfil the Luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49981:61"/>
               <table>
                  <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE SEVERAL CHAPTERS.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Page</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. I. A</hi> Summary Account of the Laws made againſt profuſe, idle, cuſtomary and expenſive Tipling; and againſt ſinful, cuſtomary and profane Drunkenneſs; and againſt keeping Places or Houſes of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Games.</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> An Account of ſome Texts of Scripture, ſhewing the ſad Conſequences and Effects that attend the cuſtomary, ſinful and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane practiſe of profuſe Quaffing and Drunkenneſs.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49981:61"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of ſeveral exemplary Judgments, both Ancient and Modern, Foreign and Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, of God's ſevere Juſtice inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cuſtomary, preſumptuous, and profane ſinful Drunkards.</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> A Compendium of the Laws made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt profane, idle, cuſtomary Swearing and Curſing.</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Some Texts of Scripture, ſhewing the Odiouſneſs and Danger of profane, cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Swearing and Curſing.</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of ſeveral ſignal, fearful and amaſing Judgments of God's ſevere Juſtice, inflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon cuſtomary, profane and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Swearers and Curſers.</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> An Abſtract of the Laws made againſt the Profanation of the Lord's Day, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Sunday,</hi> about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, diſturbing Miniſters, abſenting from the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49981:62"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the ſeveral Places or Texts of Scripture relating to the due Obſervation and Sanctifying of the Sabbath.</cell>
                     <cell>86</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> An Account of ſeveral Inſtances of God's ſevere Juſtice, and Puniſhments that have befaln preſumptuous, cuſtomary Profaners of the Lord's Day, commonly called <hi>Sunday.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>91</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> A brief Account of the Laws made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vitious and debauched Men, and lewd Women, about getting Baſtards.</cell>
                     <cell>103</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the ſeveral Places of Scripture threatning Judgments, or forbidding A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Fornication, Incontinency, Laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs and Whoredom, and ſhewing God's Anger and Diſpleaſure againſt ſuch profane Wickedneſs.</cell>
                     <cell>106</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> An Account of ſome Perſons ſignally puniſhed by Almighty God, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and wicked Vice of Whoring, and luſtful Incontinency.</cell>
                     <cell>113</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49981:62"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Lately printed for and ſold by</hi> John Harris <hi>at the</hi> Harrow <hi>in</hi> Little-Britain.</head>
            <p>THE Secret Hiſtory of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> from the Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. down to the Abdication of the late K. <hi>James.</hi> Writ at the Requeſt of a Noble Lord, and conveyed to him in Letters by—late Secretary Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Marqueſs of <hi>Louvois,</hi> who by that means had the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of all the Private Minutes between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> for many Years. The whole conſiſting of Secret Memoirs, which have hitherto lain conceal'd, as not being diſcoverable by any other hand. Publiſh'd from the Original Papers. By D. <hi>Jones,</hi> Gent. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Continuation of the Secret Hiſtory of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> from the Abdication of the late King <hi>James,</hi> in 1688. to the Year 1697. Together with the Tragical Hiſtory of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> from the firſt Riſe of that Family, in the Year 1068, down to the death of her late Majeſty Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of Bleſſed Memory. By <hi>D. Jones,</hi> Gent. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God's Judgment againſt Whoring. Being an Eſſay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a General Hiſtory of it, from the Creation of the World, to the Reign of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> (which, according to common Computation, is 5190 Years) and from thence down to the preſent Year 1697. Being a Collection of the moſt Remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Inſtances of Uncleanneſs, that are to be found in Sacred or Profane Hiſtory during that time. With Obſervations thereon, Price 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concubinage and Poligamy diſproved: Or, the Divine Inſtitution of Marriage betwixt one Man and one Woman on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aſſerted. In anſwer to a Book, writ by <hi>John Butler,</hi> B. D.
<pb facs="tcp:49981:63"/>
called his Caſe, lately preſented by the Grand Jury of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> wherein he mentions 'tis lawful to keep a Concubine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Political Miſchiefs of Popery: Or, Arguments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating. (1.) That the Romiſh Religion ruins all thoſe Countries where 'tis eſtabliſhed. (2.) That it occaſions the loſs of above 200 Millions of Livres, or 16 Millions Sterlin <hi>per Annum</hi> to <hi>France</hi> in particular. (3.) That if Popery were aboliſh'd in <hi>France,</hi> that Kingdom would become incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly more Rich and Populous; and the King's Revenues would advance above 600 Millions of Livres <hi>per Annum.</hi> (4.) That it is impoſſible that <hi>France</hi> ſhould ever be Reeſtabliſh'd, while Popery is their National Religion. By a Perſon of Quality, a native of <hi>France;</hi> Author of the Deſolation of <hi>France</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated; Dedicated to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Revelation <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nveiled:</hi> Or, an Eſſay towards the diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I. When many Scripture Prophecies had their Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, and turned into Hiſtory. II. What are now fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. III. What reſt ſtill to be fulfilled. With an <hi>Appendix,</hi> proving that <hi>Pagan Rome</hi> was not <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 17. and that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be converted. By <hi>Samuel Petto,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Sudbary</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6. <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Modern Relations of Matter of Fact concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Witches, and Witchcraft upon the Perſons of People. To which is prefixed a Meditation concerning the Mercy of God, in preſerving us from the Malice and Power of Evil An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: Written by the late Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hale,</hi> upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Tryal of ſeveral Witches before him. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some General Conſiderations offered, relating to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Trade: and intended for its Help and Improvement. By <hi>T. T.</hi> Merchant. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mathematical Divinity: Or, a Plain Demonſtration from the Holy Scriptures, that the Times of this World were foreap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham:</hi> And determined to be according to the Meaſure of the Age and Fulneſs of Chriſt. Kept Secret ſince the World began, but is now made
<pb facs="tcp:49981:63"/>
plain upon XII. Tables, in a Solar Calendar, as familiar to the Underſtanding as any common Almanack. With full proof that this is the laſt Generation, which ſhall not paſs away till all things be fulfilled, and the Gates of Righteouſneſs be opened. Being the Reſult of many Years Study. By <hi>Elias Palmer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Apology for Congregational Divines: Againſt the charge of, 1. <hi>Criſpianiſm,</hi> or <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi> 2. Countenancing Incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Tradeſmen, as Preachers. 3. Cauſeleſs Separation from Publick Worſhip. Under which Head are Publiſhed Amicable Letters between the Author and a Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmiſt (a Man of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, known every where to be ſuch) about Liturgies and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. By a <hi>Presbyterian.</hi> Alſo a Speech delivered at <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners-Hall, April</hi> 29. where Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> a Reformed <hi>Quaker,</hi> with the leave of the Lord Mayor and Biſhop, required Mr. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Elwood,</hi> &amp;c. to appear to anſwer his Charge againſt them. By <hi>Trepidantium Malleus.</hi> With an Account of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knockt down, and a Stone flung at his Head till the Blood run down his Cloaths, after a threat about ten days before, from <hi>Friend J. F.</hi> openly in the Coffee houſe, <hi>That a Church Friend of theirs, vow'd he would do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Deſcription and Uſes of a new contriv'd <hi>Eliptical</hi> and <hi>Double</hi> Dial; as alſo of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> and <hi>Aequinoxial</hi> Dial. Which ſerve to find the <hi>Latitude, Hour</hi> of the <hi>Day,</hi> the true <hi>Meridian,</hi> the <hi>Altitude, Azimuth,</hi> and <hi>Declination</hi> of the <hi>Sun;</hi> his <hi>Place</hi> in the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> of his <hi>Riſing</hi> and <hi>Setting,</hi> Length of <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Night, &amp;c.</hi> With a <hi>Scheme</hi> of each Dial Curiouſly Engraven. Very uſeful for all Seamen and Travellers, and our Curious Gentry to Set, Examine, and Adjuſt their Pendulums. <hi>Whereunto is added a Correct</hi> Table <hi>of the</hi> Latitude <hi>of the moſt Eminent</hi> Cities <hi>and</hi> Towns <hi>in Europe; as alſo a</hi> Table <hi>of</hi> Equati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. By <hi>Tho. Tuttell,</hi> Mathematical Inſtrument maker, at the <hi>King's-Arms</hi> and <hi>Globe</hi> at <hi>Charing-Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49981:64"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Lately printed for and ſold by</hi> A. Bell <hi>at the</hi> Croſs-Keys <hi>and</hi> Bible <hi>in</hi> Cornhil, <hi>near</hi> Stocks-Market.</head>
            <p>THE General Hiſtory of <hi>England</hi> both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, from the earlieſt Accounts of Time to the Reign of his preſent Majeſty King <hi>William</hi> III. Taken from the moſt Antient Records, Manuſcripts and Hiſtorians. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Lives of the Kings, and Memorials of the moſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Perſons both in Church and State. Vol. I. By <hi>James Tyrrel</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> Fol. Price 1 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Detection of the Court and State of <hi>England</hi> during the 4 laſt Reigns, and the <hi>Interregnum;</hi> conſiſting of private Memoirs <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein are many <hi>Secrets</hi> never before made publick; as alſo a more impartial Account of the Civil Wars in <hi>England</hi> than has yet been given. By <hi>Rog. Coke</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> The 3d Edition. Price 7 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Abridgment of Sir <hi>Walter Ral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh</hi>'s Hiſtory of the World, in 5 Books. 1. From the Creation to <hi>Abraham.</hi> 2. From <hi>Abraham</hi> to the Deſtruction of the Temple of <hi>Solomon.</hi> 3. From the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon.</hi> 4. From <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> to the Race of <hi>Antigonus.</hi> 5. From the eſtabliſhment of <hi>Alexander</hi> until the Conqueſt of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Macedon</hi> by the <hi>Romans.</hi> To which is added his Premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Princes. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A compleat Hiſtory of <hi>Europe:</hi> Or, a View of the Affairs thereof, Civil and Military, from the beginning of the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> 1676, to the Concluſion of the Peace at <hi>Reſwick,</hi> 1697. Including the Articles of the former, and the ſeveral Infringements of them; The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Wars; The forming of the Grand Confederacy; The Revolution in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. With a particular Account of all the Actions by Sea and Land on both ſides, and the Secret Steps towards a Peace, both before, as well as during the laſt Negotiation. The whole intermix'd with Original Letters, Papers and Memoirs, never before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd. Among others are ſeveral Letters between the <hi>Emperor,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> K. of <hi>Poland,</hi> Count <hi>Staremburg, Grand Vizier,</hi> &amp;c. relating to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Wars: The Speeches of the Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> Col. <hi>Sidney,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s and <hi>Argile</hi>'s Declarations. The Bill of Excluſion; the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Declarations:
<pb facs="tcp:49981:64"/>
The Claim of Rights for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at <hi>Reſwick,</hi> with the Articles of Peace at large. Written by a Gentleman, who kept an Exact Journal of all Tranſactions for above theſe 20 Years. Price 6 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning the Power of the Magiſtrate, and the Rights of Mankind in Matters of Religion. With ſome Reaſons in particular for the Diſſenters not being oblig'd to take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Teſt but in their own Churches, and for a General <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalization. Together with a Poſtſcript in anſwer to the Letter to a Convocation-man. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Joannis Clerici Ars Critica, in qua ad Studia Linguarum Latinæ, Graecæ, &amp; Hebraicæ via munitur; Veterum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> emendan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum, &amp; Spuriorum Scriptorum à Genuinis dignoſcendorum ratio traditur. <hi>In</hi> 2 <hi>Vol. Price</hi> 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Rational and Speedy Method of attaining to the Latin Tongue. In 2 parts. The firſt containing ſuch Precepts as are common to all Languages. The ſecond what is more peculiar to the Latin Tongue. The whole being fitted to the meaneſt Capacities, not only thoſe of riper Years, but any Child that can read Engliſh, may by this Method in a little time arrive at a greater degree of Knowledg than is uſually attain'd after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years Drudgery in the common Road. Moſt Logical Terms being in this Treatiſe alſo explain'd, the Art of Reaſoning may be perfectly learn'd without much farther trouble. By <hi>A. Lane</hi> M. A. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Art of Memory: A Treatiſe uſeful for all, eſpecially ſuch as are to ſpeak in publick. By <hi>Marius</hi> D' <hi>Aſſigny,</hi> B. D. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scotland</hi>'s Sovereignty aſſerted. Being a Diſpute concerning Homage, againſt thoſe who maintain that <hi>Scotland</hi> is a Fee Liege of <hi>England,</hi> and that the King of <hi>Scots</hi> owes Homage to the King of <hi>England.</hi> By Sir <hi>Tho. Craig.</hi> Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Short-hand yet ſhorter; or the Art of <hi>Short-writing</hi> advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a more ſwiſt, eaſy, regular, and natural Method than hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto. By <hi>G. Ridpath.</hi> The 2d Edition. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Artamenes,</hi> or the Grand <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that famous Romance. In 10 Books. By <hi>Monſ. de Scudery.</hi> Engliſh'd by <hi>F. G.</hi> Adorn'd with various Sculptures. Price 25 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chamberlain</hi>'s Midwiſery, the third Edition. Price 4 <hi>s.</hi> Bound in Calf. Uſeful for Chirurgions and Midwives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rutherford</hi>'s Letters. Price 3 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:49981:65"/>
The Fulfilling of the Scriptures for confirming Believers, and convincing Atheiſts, with rare Hiſtories of the Works of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Perſons in the Church of God. The 3d Edition. By <hi>Robert Fleming.</hi> Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preſent State of <hi>England</hi> as to Coin and publick Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. In 3 parts. Treating of the Neceſſity of more Money, and of Ways and Means to procure it; of raiſing its value, againſt which the oppoſite Prejudices, as injurious to King, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and People, with Mr. <hi>Lock</hi>'s chief Poſitions, are refuted by demonſtrable Reaſon and Matter of Fact. By <hi>J. Hodges.</hi> Price 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Help to Prayer: or a Direction how to perform that holy Duty, that it may be well-pleaſing to God. With Prayers for Morning and Evening. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> By <hi>T. Knaggs,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>The Providences of God towards this Nation in introducing the True Religion. The 2d Edition. By the late <hi>Slingsby B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thil</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning a <hi>Vacuum;</hi> wherein is endeavoured to be demonſtrated, that a <hi>Vacuum Interſperſum</hi> runs through the World, and is more or leſs in all Bodies. By a Lover of the Corpuſcular Philoſophy. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gauging and Meaſuring made Eaſie: being a brief Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of meaſuring of Surfaces and Solids after a more conciſe and intelligible Manner than commonly practiſed. Containing, Firſt, The moſt Material Propoſitions of Geometry, relating to Menſuration. 2dly. The way of Meaſuring Surfaces. 3dly. The way of Meaſuring Solids, whether it be Timber, Stone, or Liquids, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> after a moſt exact Method. Very uſeful for all Lovers of Art; ſuch as G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ugers, Meaſurers, Painters, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters, Joyners, Maſons, Bricklayers, and Glaziers. Price <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ars Chirurgiea,</hi> a Compendium of the Theory and Practice of Chirurgery. In Seven Books. By <hi>William Salmon,</hi> M. D. In 2 Vol. Price 10 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Militia Reform'd; or an eaſy Scheme of Furniſhing <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with a conſtant Land Force, capable to prevent or to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due any Foreign Power; and to maintain perpetual Quiet at Home, without endangering the Publick Liberty. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Letter to a Member of Parliament, ſhewing that a reſtraint on the Preſs is abſolutely in conſiſtent with the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and dangerous to the Liberties of the Nation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49981:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
